<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God magnified, man dethroned presented to the Parliament, and synod of England : who sit as if judges for saints, as if leaders, and guides unto the generation of Jesus Christ, the body of the communion of God / by W. Bray.</title>
            <author>Bray, William, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R159</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12877329</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12877329</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94878</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29268)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94878)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 731:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God magnified, man dethroned presented to the Parliament, and synod of England : who sit as if judges for saints, as if leaders, and guides unto the generation of Jesus Christ, the body of the communion of God / by W. Bray.</title>
                  <author>Bray, William, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Omniscience.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94878:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>God Magnified, <hi>MAN</hi> DETHRONED: Preſented to the PARLIAMENT, And SYNOD of England: Who ſit as if Judges for Saints, as if Leaders, and Guides unto the Generation of Jeſus Chriſt, the Body of the Communion of God.</p>
            <p>By W. BRAY.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>ISA. 9.15, 16.</bibl> The ancient and honourable he is the Head: the Prophet that teacheth lies, he is the Tayl. For the Leaders of this people cauſe them to erre, and they that are led of them are deſtroyed.</p>
               <bibl>MAT. 21.13, 14, 15, 16.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <bibl>JOB 20.26.</bibl> A Fire not blown ſhall conſume him, it ſhall go ill with him that is left in his Tabernacle. The heaven ſhall reveal his iniquity, and the earth ſhall riſe up againſt him.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>JOB 36.22.</bibl> Behold God exalteth by his power, who teacheth like him?</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>JOB 21.22, 34.</bibl> Shall any teach God knowledge, ſeeing he judgeth thoſe that are on high? How then comfort ye me in vain, ſeeing in your anſwers there remaineth falſhood?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:94878:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94878:2"/>
            <head>TO The High Court OF PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving by experience beheld God, and in ſeeîng God have ſeen man alſo, I deſire to ſpeak a word or two unto you, as not looſing my life unto the death, for I deſire more and more to be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and transformed into the Image of Jeſus manifeſted in the fleſh, and to live by the Faith of the Son of God in the Spirit. I have now ſeen man, the perfection of the earths Creation to be vanity, and his wayes to be as mutable as the wind, which is ſometimes Eaſt, and ſometimes Weſt, ſometimes North, and ſometimes South: and now I deſire to lie low before the God of the whole earth, and to lay aſide all voluntary humility, and worſhipping of Angels or men: I have ſeen many writings, and I have heard many tongues which have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to hinder the pure flamings of the Eternal God; even the God, the King, and Judge. The pure Scepter is in the hand of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality and Immutability, that can make the light to ſhine in the darkneſs; ſo that darkneſs ſhall not withſtand or comprehend the power of its infiniteneſs. There is much contending for victorie over one anothers cenſcience in the world, &amp; the root of ſuch endeavor for a preſent Conformity proceed from your Synod which you have choſen, who would (if they could) fain be riding on others, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Image of God in others a ſlave, a ſervant to their fallible &amp; fallibly interpreted reſults, whereas the walkings of the viſible man
<pb facs="tcp:94878:3"/> ſhould alone proceed from the pure power and teachings of the inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble God, both as to God and to man, (if we walked as he alſo walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.) The Gods of the Nations they are all Idols, vanity, a lie, and a ſhadow, though I remember I have read it was an opinion of old.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quicquid Humus, Pelagus, Coelum, miſerabile gignit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Id dixere deos, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What ever Heavens Sea, and Land begat,</l>
               <l>Hils, Sea, and Rivers, God was this and that.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Me thinks I ſee ſenſibly and experimentally (praiſed be the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercies) that the Saints ſit by the River of Babylon, and weep when they have the remembrance of Sion, and may yet ſtill do, if the Lord give power any longer to the enemie and oppreſſor: then they that carry us away captive, will require of us a ſong, and they that made exile or baniſhment our portion (as a Synodean Miniſter (ſo called) told me there was no other way for Sectaries) will revile us exceedingly, and ſay, race, race them even to the ground; and they that waſte us, will require of us mirth, ſaying, ſing us one of the ſong of Zion. But if we have not the Lord with us, God with us, How ſhall we ſing the Lords ſong in a ſtrange Land? <hi>Pſal. 137.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi> verſes.</p>
            <p>Me thinks it ſhould be a buſineſs of high concernment to you to offend one of the littele ones of the Father, (which you may doe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither you, nor your teachers are infallible) leſt you be found fighters againſt God (as God is in Ieſus) and crucifiers of the body of love, and complacency. But if you are, and if you are to me, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifiers, I deſire to imbrace the Croſs, as my Fathers Crown to me, I deſire to ſee the Croſs, and Crowne, from one ſupreame cauſe, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and will, I ſhall be glad if the Father will accompt me worthy (when I have no ground to accompt my ſelfe ſo) to ſuffer for his ſake: if you ſhall have the Crown any longer, yet know this, that your crown, your dominion, is not an everlaſting dominion, the people of the moſt high God ſhall appear more palpably, as God, with them in the inmoſt man, and then God ſhall be palpably exalted, and man dethroned.</p>
            <p>The inviſible God, and ſubſtance, hath carried me out to write theſe things, and hath anſwered all objections (though many) of
<pb facs="tcp:94878:3"/> fleſh, hell, and death, ſo that to me, to will and to do, is God, ſo that all, or any thing ſhall be to me gaine and immortall advantage. In fine, is not particular, fleſhly intereſt, the God of the world: is there, not a generall acting, judging, cenſuring and condemning, without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible judgment, and Teſtimonys and have not men thrown downe Epiſcopacy, to ſet up tyrannicall dominering Presbyterie, <hi>muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to nomine tantum.</hi> And is not formall Philoſophie, vaine deceipt, traditions of men, and rudiments of the world, the great Argument that ſwayes, witneſs many men who write many elaborate Volumes, and the continuall man-teachings of preiſts to Counſells: do not the Preiſts of the nation endeavour to blow the bellows of contention; and to divide deare friends, becauſe of difference in judgment, ſo that as one <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> one of they Fathers, <hi>Tempeſtate contentionis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renitas charitatis obnubilatur.</hi> In the tempeſt of contention the ſerenity of charity is over-clouded: may not Epiſcopalls, Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Independents ſit all under their owne Vines, and Fig-trees, and yet live lovingly one with another, one to another be contraries, &amp; yet be contraries in the ſpirit of love, and mekeneſs forbearing &amp; forgiving one another; may not every one walk in the light of his God, according to the propheſie; And the Saints walke in the light of the Lord their God: ſurely if all that talke of Chriſt, of that anoinment, were really poſſeſt in the glorie of it, man would not be any thing, but God would be all in all: I cannot hold my peace, I am <hi>Idem calamo quod in mente,</hi> I deſire you to excuſe me (if you can) that I have been ſo bold (according to the common denomination of bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) God hath condeſcended to ſpeak to me, and I have ſpoken to God, and his Teſtmony is ſure; why ſhould not you condeſcend, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture God may give you an inviſible dart, to think on temperance, and judgment to come: So I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours humble Servant if you walke according to the pure light of nature, and if you ſhall ſtand for ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and mercy in the Land.</hi> W. Bray.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:94878:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94878:4"/>
            <head>Nationall Aſſemblie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU that endeavour to make your ſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned, and to exalt God with your ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, you that conſult and endeavour to make the places of Saints too ſtraight, and to binde up the ſpirit of God to your formality, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and bounds. You that hear the children that you have loſt ſay in your ears, the place is too ſtraight for us, give place to us that we may dwell, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26. You that ſay in your hearts, who hath begotten me theſe? ſeeing you have loſt your children, and you are and will become deſolate; and who hath brought up theſe? theſe, where have they been? will you make the broad places ſtraight? will you comprehend God in a narrow compaſs of a man, of a Synod? will you compaſs the incompaſſable? will you compare with the incomparable? Oh you cannot! Do you think that God hath no other Ornament then a Directorie, to adorn a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which he means to reform? If he hath ſuch a minde, ſurely he hath. Do you think that he who hath rivers of all ſorts, and waters of glory, and of varietie to change his Creation by Ieſus Chriſt, and according to Ieſus Chriſt, hath but your ſtream? But that one current of yours which you intend to make to run in the veins of the heavens, and of the earth if you can? Surely you are deceived, God will, I am confident dry up your River, and make your fiſh to ſtink, and die for thirſt. If you have a Jaſper, do you think all muſt have Jaſpers; may not another have a Saphir? Yes truly, whether you have, or have not a Jaſper, if you have a Saphir, may not another have a Chalcedony? If you have an Emerauld, may not another have a Sardonyx? If you have a Sarduis, may not another enjoy a Chryſolite? if you have a Topar, may not another enjoy a Chryſophraſus? If you have a Jacynth, may not another have an Amethyſt? <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.19. If you have, or be any of theſe, ſurely it would be ſatisfaction
<pb facs="tcp:94878:5"/> enough to you. If you have the light of the Sun freely given you, will you endeavour to deſtroy him that hath but the light of the Moon? will you deſpiſe the day of ſmall things? Have you freely received, and will you force another to walk as you walk when he hath not received? You that were overcome your ſelves, (if you have truly overcome evill and Hereſie) will you have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Conquerour then the brightneſs of the Fathers glorie? Is it not your darkneſs and inconſiderateneſs, to ſay in your heart, who hath begotten theſe? Do you think you muſt be perpetuall Fathers? ſhall Saints be alwaies taught of fallible, mutable, vain man? would you not have God to beget how he pleaſeth, and when he pleaſeth? Oh vain man! why contendeſt thou with thy maker, the holy one of Iſrael? Thou canſt not prevail, thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver madeſt a hair of thine own head, thou never addeſt a Cubit to thine own ſtature: He that walks in the circuit of heaven laughs thee to ſcorn, and hath thee in deriſion daily. Doeſt thou think God can bring none forth, but ſuch as thou willeſt? can teach no other way, but ſuch as thou teacheſt? can have no other Terms but ſuch as thou underſtandeſt, comprehendeſt, ſtudieſt, and contriveſt? If that inviſible God, and eternall ſubſtance doth begin to ſet up his Standard to the people, &amp; to lift up his hand to the Gentiles, and to make Kings nurſing Fathers, and Queens nurſing mothers; Wilt thou inſtigate the Magiſtracy, the Kings, the powers of the world in the high places, to binde the people of God (though under another notion) in chains of death and darkneſs? Doeſt thou think that Kings, Queens, and Magiſtrates muſt be only nurſing fathers and mothers unto you, muſt honour the God of Heaven and earth only in you, and lick up the duſt of your feet? In the conſideration of theſe things, I am caſt into admiration of infinitie. Oh boundleſs God and binding man! Oh boundleſs God! that meaſureſt all things, comprehendeſt all things, who haſt infiniteneſs in all thy true variety; let not thy Saints be aſhamed to wait for thee. Oh Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperlative binding God! who art able to bind Synods, Counſels, Powers of the world, in chains and fetters of Iron; that have bound the people, &amp; deceived the Nations a great ſpace, manifeſt thy ſelf, that thou bindeſt and looſeſt, and art able to reſtrain the bindings of man, as well as to unlooſe after thou haſt given him
<pb facs="tcp:94878:5"/> power to binde. And if thou haſt an intent that this Synod ſhall be a ſcourge, or means of a ſcourge to thy people, as well as other Synods (formerly called Convocations, or other names) do thou ſay to thy Saints in the ſpirit of underſtanding; Where is the fury of former oppreſſors? and am not I the Lord thy God? and is not my name the Lord of Hoſts, who have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the Sea, whoſe waves roared? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.15. Say thou to thy people, as thou ſaidſt of old, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Ye have ſold your ſelves for nought, and ye ſhall be redeemed without money, though they that rule over you make you to howle, and cauſe the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of God to blaſpheme the Lord every day. But let thy people know, it is thou that ſpeakeſt, even thou.</hi> I am confident Synod, the thoughts of God are not your thoughts, neither are your waies, the waies of the Lord, for as the heavens are higher then the earth, ſo are the waies of the triumphant God, and the thoughts of the triumphant God higher then yours, and you may miſs of your aime in your generation: but I rejoyce you keep your Crown, Power, Kingdom, and Glorie ſo long as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will: Synod reade, perhaps you may know and underſtand, 56 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. &amp; 57 <hi>Iſa.</hi> Whoſe Chapter may appertain to thee in thy own underſtanding, and the 13 <hi>Ezekiel</hi> &amp; 14 <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 9, 10. &amp; 41 <hi>Iſa.</hi> &amp; 10 <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> &amp; 23 <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> &amp; the 26 <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> &amp; 29 <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> 8 &amp; 12 verſes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And alſo the 34 of <hi>Ieremiah</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I can (I thank the moſt High, the inviſible ſubſtance) make parallels, and the parallels aequipolent. Therefore though you ſhall endeavour to ſcourge me and afflict me, yet I ſhall ſee the love of the abſolute Lord, in ſcourgings and whippings. Though you ſhall ſay as others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you have ſaid, <hi>Come let us ſcourge him and afflict him, for he hath ſinned againſt the Lord;</hi> yet my glory is in the abſolute God, waſher, cleanſer, purger, diſcerner, informer, reformer, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitter, and from him I have my <hi>Quietus eſt.</hi> What though you make me an offender for a word? What though you ſhall have the Nobles, the Powers of the world, the Parliament (whom you inſtigate,) the People, to ſay, <hi>Come let us deviſe devices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, becauſe he ſpeaks of the things of God (he being not Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.)</hi> The Law ſhall not periſh from the Prieſt, nor Counſel from the Wiſe, nor the Word from the Prophet. <hi>Come let us ſmite
<pb facs="tcp:94878:6"/> him with the tongue, and let us not give heed to any of his words.</hi> Yet the abſolute Lord, non-reſpecter of perſons can give a word to the poor, as well as to the rich; to the Carpenter, to the Fiſher, as well as to the Prophet, the Prieſt, and the Levite.</p>
            <p>I rejoyce in your inſtigation of Magiſtracy, becauſe of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will, and becauſe it cauſes this operation in me, it makes me, and hath made me to ſee, if I might attain it, how I am (as really) in the beauty of the Son of righteouſneſs, who is more beautifull then the Sun, the Moon, and the Stars. And truly I am told of God (as I am perſwaded) that I ſhould not as yet one my ſelf with you, nor acknowldge you as friends, to the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and glory of God in Ieſus Chriſt. If I ſhould not hold forth my contrariety, as the Father hath made me contrary to you, in love for God, in love from God, and to God; I ſhould have burning fire in my own breaſt. Would you have me know any thing of God and not ſpeak it? if I ſhould forget the Lord my maker and truſt on you, and upon you; ſurely my Lord when he looks upon me and I ſee him, would make me to lie down in ſorrow, and to weep bitterly: therefore I had rather have your frowns (who call your ſelves Teachers &amp; Fathers) then my reall, abſolute, &amp; immutable Fathers. Will you ſcourge me, or afflict me, or inſtigate Magiſtracy, if at any time I ſhall declare the ſweetneſs of God? Shall I be in the garden of variety, and not ſpeak of it? would you have none be in the garden but your ſelves? would you have none other but your ſelves (though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are in the garden) to ſpeak of the things they ſee and hear? Do you know the root and the ground of Gods wiſdom? Do you know all the branches of Eternity? Do you know the God of Dominion? Will you not let him ſave whom he will, and condemn whom he pleaſeth? Will you aſſume to make a man know, before he muſt truly know; and underſtand, before he muſt truly underſtand? Are not the times and the ſeaſons in the heavens and the earth, for the fathers accompliſhments? Muſt not the heavens and the earth hear his voyce when he ſpeaks with an intention that it ſhall hear, know, and underſtand.</p>
            <p>I was lately caſt into a conſideration of the incomprehenſible od, even of God (who is acknowledged by you generally to be <hi>Cauſa Cauſarum</hi>) and alſo of vain, weak, inconſiderable, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical,
<pb facs="tcp:94878:6"/> Sophiſtical formal, in fine, ſenſuall man. I was thinking how ſmall a particular creature of God I was, and how little of the viſible world I could comprehend in the hollow of my hand, and then I conſidered, and ſaid, ſurely it would be an admired thing, if a Synod, if a man, if men, if a few men ſhould make a Law, or procure a Law, Ordinance, or Declaration to be made, that a man that could not comprehend the heavens and the earth, or the glorious viſible things of God in the hollow of his hand, ſhould be accounted an Heretick. All rationall men in the world, and thoſe that are only rationall would think it a fooliſh Ordinance, an inconſiderate Law. Would you have a Law made then, that he that cannot comprehend (or comprehend as you would have him comprehend) the inviſible things of that inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, indiviſible God, ſhall be accounted an Heretick. O ſurely if you had faith, you would be glad to have it to your ſelves, and you would manifeſt it, with the glory of its pure ſelf, and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed being: ſurely if you had faith to remove mountains, you would have more love to Hereticks (as you call them) and leſs bitterneſs. But it ſatisfies me that God can roul the heavens and the earth together like a ſcrowl, and bring it into the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row compaſs of a mans hand, if he will, and manifeſt himſelf to whom he will, and when he pleaſeth, and you are not maſters of him. He alwaies comprehends, and he can ſo be ſeen to mans capacity if he will; and he can and doth comprehend not to be ſeen if he will; he is not like to man, one little particular of Gods varieties; he can feel us, and we ſhall not be ſenſible of it; and ſee us, and we ſhall not ſee him; though he be within, and without; upon the right, and upon the left; before, and behinde. Suppoſe you have ſeen Lillies, but another hath ſeen Roſes, and another hath ſeen flowers of other natures and kinds: will you make a Law, or endeavor to have a Law made, that all muſt ſay they have ſeen Lillies, and nothing but Lillies; when they have not ſeen Lillies at all, but Roſes, or other of Gods diverſities? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, ſuppoſe you have been in the garden of God, did you get in by the ſword, by violence, by power, by ſleight of hand, by wit &amp; policie, by Logick and Phyloſophie? what muſt others do that have not your Logick and Phyloſophie? but truly I think the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſword of the incomprehenſible God will keep you out with
<pb facs="tcp:94878:7"/> your Logick, and prevail with you, and over your Philoſophie, and truly, immutably, and ſubſtantially cry, <hi>Victoria</hi> Again, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you have been in the garden of God, and ſeen the fragrant flowers, the ſweet beams of Divine Light; your names written in heaven: ſuppoſe you have the witneſs of Jeſus in your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, will you endeavour to have a Law made, that all that will not beleeve you, may be burnt with fire, may be impriſoned, may be baniſhed, may be ſawen aſunder, may not trade &amp; traffique in the kingdoms of the world, which are the Lords? Surely if you were truly taken up with thoſe beauties in your ſelves, you would not deſire that fire ſhould come down from heaven to deſtroy others much leſs make a fire your ſelves to conſume them.</p>
            <p>Again, ſuppoſe that a multitude, or many now in theſe daies ſhould ſee Jeſus Chriſt, ſhould enjoy the inviſible teachings of God in the inward man, ſhould ſpeak of it, or preach it: would it not be a Phariſaicall envious trick to endeavour to rebuke ſuch Diſciples: if they ſhould cry <hi>Hoſanna, Hoſanna,</hi> bleſſed is he that commeth in the name of the Lord in the inward man? May not Chriſt ſay, if theſe ſhould hold their peace, the ſtones would immediatly cry out <hi>Luke</hi> 19.37, 38, 39. When the incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible pleaſantneſs of the ſpirit is manifeſted, from enjoyment, it would be never the worſe if it were by all the people, if in the ſtreets, if upon the houſe tops. But I know that Scribes and Phariſees and high Prieſts will murmur at this, and pray, and faſt, that Chriſt may rebuke this, but Chriſt will not; and therefore Aſſemblie, though I have been held in chains of darkneſs a great while, and though held in the grave as it were; yet when the eternall God to my underſtanding, and with his flame inflames, and zeal makes me zealous, and in his time makes me to ſerve him, I deſire it in that time when he wils, and alone in that time when he wils and untill that time I may ſay, from my ſelf, to my ſelf, and to you, <hi>Ne ſutor ultra crepidam.</hi> But when he will inflame me to ſpeak in the underſtanding, I deſire not to value the powers of the world; whether within me, with me, or without me: For I deſire to be a ſervant to the moſt high God, though bonds and afflictions ſhall waite for me. And ſo with my reſpects to you, as to men, men ſubject to infirmities, and
<pb facs="tcp:94878:7"/> paſſions, fallible men: And alſo deſiring the father alone (if it be the fathers pleaſure) that I may whileſt I live (under the appointed power and Authority of the World) be more and more drawn up into the life Supereminent in a way of peaceableneſs, (though I live in unpeaceable, unquiet, unholy, ungodly Authority, and Power) and quietneſs, in all godlineſs and honeſty, I reſt:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Hoping I am, and ſo ſhall be</hi> A Servant to the abſolute Lord, though I ſhall be perſecuted for the ſame, <hi>W. Bray.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94878:8"/>
            <head>To the Impartiall and Partiall READERS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoever thou art, under what name ſoever thou wouldeſt be accounted, and eſteemed amongſt men, if thou art free to reade, let it be as if there were no diſtinction of names by man which tend to divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp; fleſhly contention; but if thou &amp; I are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed in the true nature of diſtinction, (as of, and in two bodies in oppoſition, deſigned, and brought forth by the eternall God) I know we ſhall be contraries, though in ſome meaſure, I can ſay, I have the ſpirit of teſtimonie, the ſpirit of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, yet, I can ſay, I am nothing at all, neither do I deſire to be any thing, but what God will, and whatſoever I am, or am made to be, that God may be all in all. Perhaps I ſhall lead thee through varietie of objects, which thou wilt like, and diſlike, but whoſoever thou art, I hope I ſhall not be offended with thee (being in it kept through the power of God) if thou diſlikeſt, nor the more affected, if thou likeſt, for thy liking, or diſliking, commends me not, neither diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends me unto God. But his Teſtimony unto me, with me, for me, in me, is free, and true, even higher if poſſible, then perfection can ſtyle it, <hi>Non ab homine teſtimonium accipio,</hi> I receive not mans record, I care not for mans teſtimony. I have directed this enſuing treatiſe to the nationall Miniſters (ſo called) perhaps you will expect they ſhould confirme the words they have ſpoken, and preached unto you: If that miniſteriall Aſſembly, and thoſe godly divines, (ſo called and eſteemed) will not vouchſafe or condeſcend to give me an anſwer, I ſhould be unwilling to be a Proſelite to ſuch men. But my comfort is, that he that inhabits eternity will diſcourſe with me in the inner man, within my owne vail, when I ſhall not be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or accounted worthy to come within a thouſand foot of a Synod. I have read, that <hi>Mahomet</hi> when he had publiſhed his Alcaron, no man muſt comment, dare to diſpute, or call in queſtion any part of it, be it never ſo abſurd, incredible, fabulous, and ridiculous, it
<pb facs="tcp:94878:8"/> muſt be beleived, implicite, no man muſt contradict it upon paine of death, threats, terrours, affrights, tyranny, are their means to keep men in obedience, Preiſts and polititions do delude the whole world now at this day: Such men as have, and do read <hi>Machiavell and Tacitus</hi> are the men that act to the <hi>bene eſſe</hi> of a Common-wealth, and muſt alſo (as they ſuppoſe) act in dominion and authority over the Church of God The Prieſts talke much of the ſpirit in their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and preachings, yet none other muſt upon paine of damnation, or hereſie, at leaſt; others if they preach it, or declare it, muſt be termed by them, <hi>Enthuſiaſts,</hi> and what not. Can we exclaime thus <hi>O Feſtus dies hominis!</hi> If that the light of reaſon only were not ſtifled, and choaked in the world by the nationall Preiſts and their Proſelites pretended divinity men would not be ſo much deceived. Do not take notice of names, as Epiſcopall, Preſbiter, and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, for a man may uſe either of them, without wrath or malice, a man may ſay unto you all, do as you would be done by. Let God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone (if you can) to deſtroy all unrighteouſneſs, and to add Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits to our ſtatures; whoſoever thou art, if thou art righteous, thou canſt not hinder anothers wickedneſs, and fals, untill God wills it; ſo if thou art wicked, thou canſt not hinder anothers righteouſneſs unleſs God wills it, God hath brought forth varietie in the world, and one thing ſhall not hinder another till the Supream cauſe of all will hinder as to man, and further as to man. Methinks it would be more ſuitable to the Scriptures of an Apoſtle, if in any thing any one be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall even reveale it unto him, and that would be the ceſſation of contention in Epiſcopalls, Preſbiters, and Independents ſo called. I deſire onely to manifeſt a ſtriking at the roote of any evill, as I am ſtriken lovingly of God, the ſupreame cauſe, I deſire him alone to perfect the work in righteouſneſs, and to bring forth judgement and truth unto victory when he will, both to thee, and me. I write this unto man, not for libertie, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what grounds I have in my owne conſcience for the ſame of him, and from him, who gives and continues libertie, and holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency in a divine will, in priſon and out; I have beene under an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary temptation (of &amp; from the Devill &amp; Satan, that for the preſent hath Crowns in the world) that I might not manifeſt my ſelf in this particular way but God hath anſwered all Arguments that I can, and paradventure alſo that thou canſt make. If I ſhall be againe
<pb facs="tcp:94878:9"/> ſtriken friendly of the Saints, I deſire I may ſee it as a precious balme, and imbrace it, and in ſome of all ſee the active God in it. If I am ſtriken of others, I deſire to ſee only power, will, and authority, from the Father of conſolation: So accept this from him who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the ſervice of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God, as in the generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> W. Bray.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94878:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Emporarie Potentates,</hi> (that now are) you muſt go to the great Grave of your Fathers, even you Mutable, living, and dying Potentates, you muſt be incloſed in the Concave of the earth. You Principle Counſels the beſt of you not much better then your fathers: nay, if ſome of your fathers were extant in the Viſible life, you would hardly counterpoiſe them in a ballance: if you would ſuffer your ſelves to be weighed, you would be found too light. Oh! you ſpirituall Senſitive Synods or other Aſſemblies in the whole World: VVhat though you break out without an abſolute holy zeal of the eternall God, (but yet with zeal) with a zeal to ſet up your ſelves, or to honour eternity with the thoughts of your ſelves, with the directories of your own hearts. <hi>Interrogemus Prophetas, Interrogemus Apoſtolos, Interrogemus Scripturas, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogemus Chriſtum:</hi> Have not many of your Nationall fathers erred, not knowing the true and reall minde of the minifeſtations of that incomprehenſible God? Have not many of your fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, even you your ſelves varied from Apoſtolicall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and livings in the Spirit? If I did think Antichriſt would not lye, or if you were competent Judges of your own hearts (in this great time of your contention for Maſteries, for power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, for the ſitting in the uppermoſt Rooms of feaſts, for Judging according to your ſelves) you would tell me that you have all gone out of the way, and that you are altogether become abominable, even in the eyes of the divine inviſible preſence, as it is in the Son of the Fathers love; and alſo in your own eyes: Have not many of you endeavoured to finde out the profound, unſearchable riches of the incomprehenſible God, who is every where, in all the natures of things; and yet can hide himſelf in relation to any thing beſide himſelf, ſo that they ſhall not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94878:10"/> him? May not God work upon the Left hand, and upon the Right hand, &amp; you ſee him not? ſurely it's recorded that <hi>Job</hi> was in ſuch a condition <hi>Job</hi> 23.9. Have you not endeavoured to finde out that one indiviſible mind, that one unalterable God, as if you contained him in the hollow of your hands, in one aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, aſſembled company? <hi>Oh! then truly thoſe that you are pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to call Sectaries, of all men are moſt miſerable.</hi> Have not you thought you might finde truth's glory by the knowledge of the Etymologie of words, by your artificiall learning and parts, by finding out the fallible derivations and nationall changings of Termes? Have not your Sermons been cunningly and artificially compoſed, like <hi>Menander</hi> his two Comoedies <hi>Andria</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthia,</hi> which were very unlike in compoſition? And hath not this deceived the hearts of the people, though your ſubject mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (as you will ſay) differ little? Do not you in your great contentions endeavour to make a Uniformity in worſhip, (which you are pleaſed to call circumſtantials, or to give ſome other ſlight name to it,) and alſo an Uniformity in your ſubſtantialls; ſo that the Magiſtrates have been as the Prieſts, or the Prieſts as the Magiſtrates; and ſo Prieſts, Magiſtrates, and people have been almoſt all one? But you muſt likewiſe go to the Sepulchre of your fathers, to be intoombed, or hidden myſtically in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning Bowels of the earth, the grave of the eternall God for all. Yeſterday it was to a perſecuting Papiſt, afterwards to a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Proteſtant power, and to day is to a domineering Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Hinc illae Lachrymae,</hi> here is unſtedfaſtneſs in all our wayes, here is perſecution under 3. adulterated formes: though I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only theſe formes, I complicate other formes whatſoever they are in the world, that are not of God even the Father, as conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the body of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Give me leave to reaſon with you, and take all in good part; for I freely give in a loving conſideration: but let me tell you in this little Tract, that which I apprehend, will in the time of the inviſible, omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Father peirce you to the very heart; even ſome of you in this Generation before it paſſeth away, by that word which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures for ever. Oh thou Papiſt! haſt thou Ieſus, Ieſus, ſo much in thy mouth? Oh thou Proteſtant! haſt thou Chriſt as much in thine? and thou Presbyter haſt thou the Lord Jeſus as much in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94878:10"/> thy mouth as either of the former, to throw both down; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo that are in a form of contrariety to thee, and to make thy ſelf an abſolute Lord, an abſolute lover of thy ſelf, an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute pleaſer of thy ſelf, an abſolute liver to thy ſelf: I only give theſe names, becauſe you are capable of thoſe names you own your ſelves by, and diſtinguiſh your ſelves; and indeed are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed in the world; therefore be not offended at it.</p>
            <p>You ſpeak much of Chriſt, and your own ordinary and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent expreſſions to maintain your own <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in your mouths (nay, I think in your hearts.) You ſay indeed <hi>Interrogemus Chriſtum,</hi> but you do take councell with your ſelves, and if you, or any of you, ſhall be ſubject to the ſweet teachings of God, of the moſt holy, true, and abſolute, you will tell me hereafter, or others, if not me, or your ſelves, if not others; or be told of God that you did proclaim a Faſt, but you inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to cut of <hi>Naboaths</hi> head before hand, to ſtone poor <hi>Naboath</hi> &amp; all becauſe he will live in the inheritance of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. You will ſay that you had ſelf-contrivings, and Law-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, to deſtroy thoſe that would walk, and live, and ſpeak, as being the inheritance, and in the inheritance of the Father, of freeneſs, love, and excellencie: You will ſay that you with the will of your ſelves, and the minde of your ſelves, (though unſeeingly to you, the minde of the incomprehenſible) did make way for Stigmatizing, and Stigmatizing Informers; if you faſted from your ſelves, if you did not ask councell of your ſelves in the forms of truth; make interrogatories to your ſelves, and anſwer your own queſtions; it would be a great queſtion whether you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the voyce of God, or walked after your own premeditated Ordinances, Laws, and Deſignes. What though your Counſels, (as it is recorded of <hi>Herod</hi> in the peoples apprehenſions) do ſpeak as the Oracles of God? what though you make your ſelves ſtrong by arguments drawn from your vaſt Humane Intellects, (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the formall denomination of wiſdom and underſtanding in the world) it is all but your ſelves, it is but the high glory of an exterior and myſticall Antichriſt; it is but <hi>ad res inanes ſtudia convertere;</hi> It is that, that hath deceived all the Nations of the world, and doth deceive the people &amp; multitudes of the earth, and make them to wonder at you: and indeed it hath not only
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94878:11"/> drawn the earthly, and beguiled the ſimple, ignorant of God through deceipt, but alſo the heavenly, the Saints of the moſt high, thoſe that are in the fathers boſome, &amp; glorious teachings, even to make a Diſciple for a ſeaſon to deny his Maſter; till the ſubſtance, the inviſible, incomprehenſible God hath given them to ſee himſelf more, and alſo themſelves and others, and to ſee and live to themſelves and others leſs, and to ſee him inmoſt of all, within every vail, within whom nothing is, and without whom nothing is, or is not: is it not evident in the world, that Synods and Aſſemblies have more looked upon, and judged truth to be according to mens various argumentative varieties, according to the ſeeing of the eye, and the hearing of the ear, rather then the true and reall diſcendings of God in their own underſtandings, by the abſolute ſpirit, witneſs, Teſtimonie, or manifeſtation of the ſole ſupream?</p>
            <p>How many thouſands of adulterous voyces have the world heard and worſhiped with, even with the Supereminenteſt names of Glory? how many falſe and uncertain ſounds have the <hi>Plebei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> (ſo called by many in ſcorn) affected from a <hi>Cauſidick,</hi> or a Terreſtriall Polititian, or an affected &amp; ſelf-affecting Prieſt, when the ſound have been given by thoſe that have the power of the Aire, that are the princes, Lords, Counſellors, and Synods of the World, hath not errour been affected from them, if under glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous names, and curious expreſſions? let the Generation that is now, be Judge, Oh you Lords! you Conſellors of the earth: Oh! you Cedars in the world your Kingdome, you have inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven your ſelves into the language of the Almighty, and mixt your droſs with the precious, and ſcarce-known truths in the VVorld; But your mixture deſtroys not the ſubſtance, but the ſubſtance in the fulneſs of time ſhall deſtroy your mixture: but how many, or whether all you ſhall be ſaved in that day, I deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine not; he alone knows, before whom, all things are naked, and not vailed.</p>
            <p>Truly Potentates I ſee (when I behold him, or when I am ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made to behold him, who is the cauſe of all, and of me, that am in particular, and of what I am, whom I deſire to live unto) mans highneſs to be lowneſs; mans ſtrength, to be weakneſs; mans promiſes to be perfideouſneſs; mans liberty to be bondage;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94878:11"/> mans Communion to be far different from the Communion with the Father and the Son in the active, ſubſtantiall, immutable, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſpirit: I ſee mans truths to be vanity and a lye; mans love to be wrath, mans goodneſs and conſtancie to be all to himſelf, and man with God in his heart, as by his underſtandings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, and man with God in his mouth to carry on the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of his worldly Kingdome and glory.</p>
            <p>Truly earthly ſcourgers and Tormentors in your own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and glories, your intentions to ſcourge and afflict, do make me to looke to the interioreſt, &amp; to ſee if poſſible I can by that meaſure of glory miniſtred to me, how I am as to the great <hi>Iehovah;</hi> and how I muſt be to him, and for him and not to you, for you, nor to him for you, but that I might be all for him, and all from him if poſſibly to you, to him, that ſo I might ſee what I have been and am unto my ſelfe, But in the conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my thoughts I conſidered this with my ſelfe, I ſhall not be truely able to endure the brunt of violence, if my contrarietie be to you only with the fleſh, it is but Sathans Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf, whoſe Kingdom and glory muſt ceaſe, and muſt be demonſtrated to be vile and contemptible, for theſe two (which are but one) contraries in this ſeeming diviſion, ſhall at length finde and feele the abſolute contrary, the ſupream, and the ſupere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, the head, the Judge. In my alone ſeriouſneſs I conſidered that I had been a profeſſor (of and out of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſo called) but my profeſſion made me no Saint: for it is the alone abſolute and reall ſanctification in the Spirit that muſt make me a Saint &amp; a profeſſor, I did finde according to the ſubſtance of exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination &amp; ſcrutiny, that my profeſſion now muſt ſurely be more then formerly; that it muſt have an abſolute life or elſe a fire would quench it, &amp; the looks of Lords would abaſh it, a priſon would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon it when I ſhould be in and out, if I ſhalbe out after I am in, it would cauſe a ceſſation, and honour and credit and preferment amongſt men would enſnare me, and with it's ſmiles would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap me: But Lord let not the Lords excellencies, mutabilities, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, in fine Vanities, intrap me, let not my profeſſion be meerly a profeſſion of the eternall and everlaſting beeing and name ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to things without me in the ſimilitude of the profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world, generally, cofuſedly, and from an exterior ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trajudiciall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94878:12"/> affection, that eternitie would comprehend me as knowingly to me (as well as knowingly to himſelfe, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends all things knowingly) in the true ſerious and reall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſanctification; and that my profeſſion may be the true and reall effluxs of ſuch a glorious comprehenſion.</p>
            <p>But Princes, Nobles, and Counſels, not worthy to be named ſo, in relation to the abſolute ſupreame; I deſire to behold a diſtance; when I am truly acted in contemplation of the Prince, the abſolute, the true, the infallible, unſpeakable; though I ſpeak of the falſe, though I ſpeak of the fallible and mutable, I deſire not to center there; I deſire only to ſpeake of the fading, and dying glories, as being United to him who comprehends the mutables, the exteriors, and the interiors, and ſpeaks of them, and to them, and give them their names and places.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Satan</hi> that Divell tempted me, and endeavoured to have Dominion over me and it preſented it ſelf to my exterior, and approached violently with curious attire, fine expreſſions, the language of the moſt High to have admittance; but the interior (I thank the Lord) had preſent recourſe to the Interioreſt, to the comprehending the myſticall God, the comprehending incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible. Me thought I had theſe things preſented me, if you will not walk according to the Law of Nobles, Lords, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates, you will be cruſhed, they will binde you in chains, will not let you live in the world, Impriſon your poor body, make you to be deſpiſed of all men, if thy profeſſion or the things thou liveſt in, &amp; knoweſt, were more generall; then thou mighteſt have ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, credit, and reputation in the profeſſion thereof, thou wouldeſt have friends in the unrighteous <hi>Mammon;</hi> the <hi>High-Prieſts,</hi> the <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſees,</hi> &amp; the Doctors of the Law are thy <hi>Antagoniſts;</hi> but then was the time for the abſolute Lord to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and his appearance cauſed contrarietie to the Lords Agent or Agents: then I (deſpiſed, contemned, inconſiderable perſon) did deſire that I might behold the abſolute Lord, and might now contend in the ſpirit, and ſpeak by the power of the higheſt, the cauſe of all cauſes, the God of all natures, the father of all ſpirits, and might now be made unwilling to ſtand before him, as being any thing; and that I might be what he will'd, and might not be what he nil'd, Abſolute ſupream, one Abſolute Counſellour,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94878:12"/> (yet more wiſe then Counſellours) let me be abaſed, ſo as in my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſement thou aboundeſt, in me, to me, though thou art incapable of abounding in thy ſelf: thou who comprehendeſt the heavens &amp; the earth the conſtellations, glories, and powers of both; let the particular, producted, viſible form and ſhape; even me in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, ſee thee who art alone praiſe-worthy If the world have a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for me, tell me that the priſon is thine, both before and when I am there; and let me know that nothing divides thee and me; for thou art indiviſible, and mayeſt, when thou wilt, be ſeen in all the natures of things. <hi>Oh thou eternall triumphant God!</hi> let me live in the wondering and admiring of thy holy, unſported fulneſs: let me not look upon ſpots any more, upon emptineſſes any more, but with the communication of thy ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs incommunicable, that is, let me not look upon things by the wiſdome of ſelf, by the ſenſuall wiſdom, the wiſdome of the fleſh; let me not look upon a lye any more to be deceived by it, to live upon it, to live to it, to be delighted in it: thou that haſt habitation and habitations, and yet haſt no habitation at all to incloſe thee, comprehend thee, inviron thee, &amp; do good unto thee; if thou haſt eternally will'd it, let me be the habitation of thy wiſdome, though a priſon ſhall be a habitation for me: <hi>Oh ſweet God!</hi> how ſweet will it be, that I ſhould be a habitation for thy inviſible, indiviſible ſelf, in the ſpirit of underſtanding: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer that Divell for me whom thou haſt made and given power to deceive, and yet haſt power to conquer him; and if thou haſt a minde that I ſhall ſpeak of thee, and acknowledge thee, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it, and then let me not fear the face of a man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils; but yet Lord let me have that courage that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to thy immutable life, and to thoſe that live unto God, and not themſelves.</p>
            <p>When I ſhall, or if I ſhall be brought before Magiſtrates, Kings, Counſellours, or Judges of the earth, let not that move me; let me not be toſſed to and fro by them, ſo as to give up or make recantation of thoſe thngs thou manifeſteſt by thy eternall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, let me be before the Magiſtrate and judge as knowingly in the preſence of the judge of Magiſtrates and Judges; and let me ſpeak as in thy preſence: Lord I have ſpoken in private of thee and to thee, and thou vouchſafeſt to reaſon with with me,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94878:13"/> and diſcourſe with me, but man is vain, man is ſenſuall, man is proud, and the lofty ones would be more lofty, then the lofty one that inhabits eternity. Wilt thou inviſible God draw me to ſpeak to thee, and furniſh me with arguments: and ſhall I be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to ſpeak of thee, to thee, in the face and hearing of a dying man? But Lords of the earth, Lords in time, I may truly ſay as in the preſence of the Lord of times and ſeaſons; <hi>Oh Lord my God!</hi> other Lords beſides thee have had Dominion over me, (have been in me the head of a deſigne) but by thee will I only make menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Temporarie Lords, Counſellours, Synods,</hi> if he that ſees would make you ſee, that ſay you ſee; if he that apprehends, would make you apprehend, you would ſee your ſelves, neither Lords to your ſelves, nor Lords to others in things concerning the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible life; you would be glad to have your ſelves dethroned, and the abſolute ſupream in all your titular, momentary glories a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone dignified, and exalted.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Mutable Dominion,</hi> what will it avail in the day of the Triumph of the abſolute perpetuall Triumphant; when ſorrow and mourning ſhall flie away from your abjects, the off-ſcum, and off-ſcouring of your worldly glory: when fears, death and Hell, when worſe then the Plagues of <hi>Egypt</hi> ſhall fall upon you, &amp; poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs you, even you that have had the pleaſures of <hi>Egypt,</hi> &amp; power given not only to your ſelves, but pleaſure in your ſelves to ſcourge the Nations, eſpecially the refining Jewels of the great God of heaven and earth.</p>
            <p>Me thinks I ſee and hear, that the <hi>Lords</hi> of the earth, the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates</hi> of the world; the praying, the preaching, the faſting, the fleſhly glories, and the ſpirits of Antichriſt (but I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs with ſome comfort, it is only during their time of dominion and whilſt their place is to be found) endeavour to deſtroy the prayers of Saints by praying, the declarations of Saints by Preaching; to deſtroy the glory of true, reall, and abſolute faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by faſting.</p>
            <p>This Nationall Interrogatory may be indeed asked; What Religion do you profeſs? May there not be a generall cry by thoſe that ſee? May there not be a Trumpet ſounded in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the World (but more eſpecially in the commonly called
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94878:13"/> houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> or <hi>England,</hi>) that ſeemingly there is a daily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to know the wayes of the moſt high; as if a Nation that did righteouſly, and did not forſake the ordinances of the great God; as if they walked according to the dictamen of the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſole ſupream, and lived according to the abſolute ſpirit of the eternall God in the truth of underſtanding: do they not ſeem to ask of God he Ordinances of Juſtice, when their own praeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated, praeordinated, fleſhly, Antichriſtian Ordinances, Lawes, and Statutes, are maintained by their fleſhly, carnall, accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power? But theſe delight in their approaching to, and by the name of the eternall God.</p>
            <p>Have we not the Monarchs, the powers of the world, of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the ſpirits of darkneſs, death, hell, and the Grave that challenge the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to his face, that inſultingly, and domineeringly, and as much as in them lie, blaſpheme the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſupream wiſdome: and would be in the place of the ſupream Cauſe; or would have the ſupream Cauſe to be their ſervant? and they to be Maſter to that eternall, abſolute, undefiled, immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table glory; as if they ſhould ſay, we have faſted and thou ſeeſt not; have we obſerved dayes and moneths and years, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt thou not? We love the Nation with our hearts, and we will preſerve the Nation with our prayers: Shall we obſerve a day, and wilt thou not obſerve both the day and us? We have not only afflicted our bodies, but our very ſouls: if bodily whippings; ſcourgings, and laſhings of our ſelves, (as many of us are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in our underſtandings) will not move thee: yet our afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſoules, &amp; piercing our ſelves through with many ſorrows, or reducing our ſelves in body &amp; ſoul into a <hi>ſuper-ſuperlative</hi> way of ſadneſs and affliction, will, muſt move thee: Wilt thou take no knowledge of this excellent daies work of ours? We came with an intent to have thee know what we would have thee know, and do, what we would have thee do againſt <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Sectaries,</hi> diſturbers of the Peace; we would have thee our ſervant, our ſlave, but we wil not ſay ſo, for that wil too much undeceive the world; if out of our own mouth we ſhould judge our ſelves, we ſhould no more binde the world in temporarie chains, and in fetters of our own deviſing. <hi>But Oh Lords! Oh you Monarchs</hi> in a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Nations! you have here in this little Tract, but an earneſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94878:14"/> of your charge drawn up; but when the interioreſt of all, when that knowing, ſeeing, and judging God, that lofty one ſhall come and judge you according to that you are within, (for you are not alwaies the ſame without that you are within) What are yee? What difference ſhall you ſee? Shall you not ſee a change, and a vaſt diſproportion betweeen a <hi>Lord,</hi> and a <hi>Lazarus</hi> that was captivated to the light and knowledg of the abſolute Lord: <hi>But Lords,</hi> or powers of the World, by what name or title ſoever diſtinguiſhed, what though in the day of your faſting you found pleaſure and delight yet it was but an exaction of your own la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; ye faſted for ſtrife and prayed for debate, and to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſs, as a Nation that did righteouſneſs, juſtice and mercie; as if you lived to the higheſt formes of truth, in relation to humanity, and likewiſe to infallible and abſolute Divinity; but in the 58 of <hi>Iſa.</hi> you may ſee your Image even by your Nationall fathers before you, when the abſolute alone ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream judge ſhall enter into judgement, and give grinding to the grinders, in giving eternall burthens to thoſe that have tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily burthened, bound and oppreſſed. O then let the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Rocks fall on us and the Hills cover us from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the judge: <hi>Oh then! Miniſters, Divines, Teachers, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigators, Inſtructers</hi> (as you ſaid of your ſelves) in righteouſneſs, what hiding place ſhall we have? But you ſay or think, it may be, that there is no ſuch thing to be expected, therefore you will take another mans word, I wiſh I could truly ſay (if it were the will of eternity) much good may it do ye.</p>
            <p>When the abſolute ſupream ſhall faſten this to your Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which as yet paſſeth away as a tale that is told unto you, 59. <hi>Iſai.</hi> Your hands are defiled with blood, and your fingers with iniquity; your lips have ſpoken lyes, you conceive miſchief, and you bring forth iniquity; you hatch <hi>Cockatrice</hi> eggs, and weave the <hi>Spiders</hi> webb: but your eggs, if they are eaten, they that eat them die; and if any with the power of life, manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and underſtanding of the Abſolute, cruſh your eggs, they break forth preſently into a viper; but when eternity will enter into judgement; when the Iſlands ſhall flie away, and the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains not be found, when the hearing of this voyce ſhall be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:94878:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh Lord, (not Lords)</hi> holy and true, doeſt thou not judge and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the earth, ſhall the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the heavens afford you any comfort? they ſhall be roll'd together like a ſcrowl: ſhall the Kings of the earth, and the great men, the richmen, &amp; the chief Captains (your ſervants) the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty men, the bond men, the freemen, the Dens, Rocks &amp; Mountains afford you comfort and ſuccour? Shall multitudes? ſhall kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reds, Nations, Tongues? ſhall power and authority? ſhall a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die? ſhall a Queen? ſhall a woman arrayed in purple, and ſcarlet colour, decked with Gold &amp; precious ſtones, with a Golden cup in her hand? <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. Shall the Merchants of the earth, with their Merchandiſe of Gold, Silver, and Precious ſtones? ſhall the fruits that your ſoul luſted after? ſhall the Shipmaſters? <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. ſhall the Parliaments? ſhall the Synods? ſhall the Committees? No ſurely Lords: <hi>Oh then!</hi> happy is he whoſe God is the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Counſellors,</hi> but earthly <hi>Polititians,</hi> when you ſhall be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned in the interiour man by the interioreſt, the all-ſeeing <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the infinite everlaſting, the abſolute Lord: VVhat are many Lords, and what are many idolized falſe Gods? when you ſhall be called Gods, and Lords, and come to be judged, arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, condemned by the abſolute non-reſpecter of perſons, as men in the inwardeſt cogitations, minde, &amp; underſtanding with thoſe aggravations that lie in the wiſdome of eternity, to make and manifeſt, your Webs ſhall not become garments, neither ſhall yee cover your ſelves with your works; for your works are works of iniquity, and the Act of violence is in your hands.</p>
            <p>But in the midſt of all my thoughts I was ſore oppreſſed in my own ſpirit, &amp; I was willing to give up my ſelf, even the exteriour &amp; the interior life to the ſupream abſolute. To live in the world I was unwilling, yet willing; for live I muſt, and in this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration live I would, ſo long as the giver or the taker pleaſeth; let him do with me what ſeemeth him good in his own eyes: But I ſaw man, or the temporary Lords in the world contending to amend; &amp; me thought I ſaw that which was mended by man, was but amended with a fancy; and that which was amended with a fancy, was lacerated and torn with another: one mans amending another in the world, in relation to the ſupereminent divine changer, amender, tranſlater, is like a ſimple Cobler his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94878:15"/> a paire of ſhooes, that may be for a fortnights or leſs (not much more) walking, will weare them out, ſo that it may be ſayed, as you were, or rather worſe then you were, for theſe amendings periſh with the uſing; therefore I may ſay, <hi>Ne ſutor ultra crepidam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which I beheld in the world, I deſired the ſupream to deſtroy in me, for I thought with my ſelf, it may be I may contein all the innormities of the whole Orb, therefore I was in fine, made to reflect upon the ſupream, and the abſolute Lord and Lawgiver; and when I by reflexion conſidered the foundation of all Generations, and I had no ſatisfaction in the apprehenſion of the life of the Generations paſt, or the life of the Generation that now is: I was reduced into the foundation, and that gave me ſome ſweet ſolacing, and ſome pleaſant refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>But in ſeeing I beheld, and in my view I ſaw the Lords of the earth had inlarged, and were ever inlarging their beds of pleaſure, to take pleaſure in their exceſs, and their temporary glories: Methought I ſaw them reſolved ſo far as mutable Lords could reſolve, to keep to their own Lawes, Statutes, Ordinances, and to make them unto themſelves, and demonſtrate it unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as if it were the abſolute, true and infallible Sabbath of reſt, and commendable by the moſt high. And when I did upon the Lords caſting me into ſerious conſideration; behold the Lord by the glimmerings of the ſupereminent and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting glory opening the Seals: I ſaw beaſts in the ſhape of men going forth conquering, and to conquer, with bows in their hands, <hi>Rev</hi> 6. And I ſaw and expected an Arrow to pierce all thoſe who held the Teſtimony of Jeſus, I ſaw the Lords and the Potentates of the Aire, thoſe that had the power of Nations and Kingdomes (ſo long as they had the Crown) go forth conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to conquer. But Lord if it be thy will, make me alſo to will to receive (if thou willeſt to give) an Arrow from that Bow. The life ſupereminent was no ſooner held out, the Seals were no ſooner opened by the eternall ſupereminent judging word; but preſently another beaſt repreſented it ſelf (ſo long as it had the Crown) to take peace from the earth, and to kill with the ſword. <hi>But Oh Lord Abſolute and Eternall!</hi> I cannot
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94878:15"/> ſay that thou wilt not reveale thy ſelf to any one, becauſe thou doeſt: not reveal thy truth to many a one; but if thou wilt reveal what thou haſt hid, and hide what thou haſt revealed, thy will be done: the generations of the world, are ſervants to thy My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall glory, and to thy incomprehenſible Majeſty; draw me up unto that ſupereminent life in the truth of apprehenſion and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that ſo I may live in that life though I am kill'd with the ſword.</p>
            <p>Alſo I ſee a further accompliſhment, and in the accompliſhing I behold even in the temporarie world, a horrible perſecution and affliction upon the exteriour formes, and natures of things: methought I ſaw violence on every ſide, perſecution and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under all formes, to ſtifle the Teſtimony: methought I ſaw the beaſt, the powers of the world, the Aire, the Kings of the earth, the great men, the rich men, and the chief Captaines, and the mighty men, (that had the temporarie Crown given them) endeavour by all waies and means poſſibly to deſtroy the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyers, and the Teſtifyers Teſtimony. Methought I ſaw the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porany and yet infernall Nobles of the earth, that wear the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentany and yet perpetuall Crown of Hell and death in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves according to the power that is committed unto them, act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſecution in one form upon the Neck of another, which is the manifeſtation of the varietie, and yet unity of that ſtate, that body of Antichriſt, Hell and death, ſword, hunger, and beaſts of the earth, even Epheſian beaſts after the manner of men: and then I ſaw the doom of thoſe that have the Teſtimony of the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: and I brake out into Admiration in my ſelf, <hi>Oh eternity!</hi> how do the Nations of the world, the Nationall powers of the world, hear, and ſee, and read, and ſeem, and would be ſuppoſed to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, yet they ſee not nor underſtand, and yet they ſuſpect not themſelves, but teach and declare of themſelves, and ſay that they are chriſtians &amp; walk in the life ſupereminent. <hi>But Nobles</hi> of the earth take this only if you can lovingly, til I am more loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inflamed, or untill the father will manifeſt himſelf more unto you, or me, even in the interioreſt in the dividing aſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, rending, and tearing in pieces of all your fleſhly deceitfull glories, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you have for many hundred years paſt, deceived the people of the earth: I am no diſputer of the world, I deſire to be <hi>Tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teltra</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:94878:16"/> and not <hi>Oedipus.</hi> I deſire not to inſinuate with you but to live to my God: the God and Lord abſolute, mercifull, holy, undefiled and eternall, I deſire only of the father that I unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; weakneſs, may live to him and with him in the interioreſt, ſublimeſt, and trueſt; and that thou worthineſs, gloriouſneſs, wouldeſt underſtandingly as to me, comprehend my particular, and do what thou wilt with me in my exterior, or in this viſible world: if thou worthineſs and truly eternall Lord, wilt ſurrend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er me up into the hands of the Lords and powers of the earth, that act in a conſtitution of perſecution: Let me in the interior ſay Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But yet Sathan</hi> that Divell tempts me; but yet me thinks I am ſurrounded and invironed in this my pilgrimage, and methinks the exteriors of the world operate, inſinuate, diſpute, and reaſon with me and tempts my exterior to conform me to its ſelf, and confound me in its ſelf: I heard a voyce in the world the other day ſaying, (very Schiſmatically, erroneouſly, and according to the witneſs of men) and denying the abſolute witneſs of the great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> denying that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying that power is given to the Son, loving, to have the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, the uppermoſt Rooms at feaſts, and in Synagogues, ſetting themſelves in the place of God: attributing that to their fallible, deceiptfull, devilliſh underſtandings, actings and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivings, that is, to be attributed to the alone ſupream; not waiting when God the abſolute changer will give repentance to thoſe that beleeve not the truth but have pleaſure in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; earneſtly contending (as they ſay) for the faith that was once delivered to the Saints, in ſuch wayes of carnallity, by ſuch carnall weapons which were not uſed in the times of that excellent, glorious, Apoſtolicall miniſtrations of God, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently denying the glorious and ſupream power of the ſpirit; giving themſelves to fornication, and going after ſtrange fleſh to deceive the Nations, deſiling the fleſh by their filthy dreaming, by impoſing ſuch things for an exterior worſhip (as if Commanders) as are not conſiſtent, with the life and glory of the Spirit in us. Whereas the fleſh of Chriſt that viſible manifeſtation of God at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> 1600 years ago, was lead according to teachings of the Divine God, deſpiſing the true and abſolute Dominion and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94878:16"/> dignities of the moſt High, ſpeaking evill of thoſe things they know not, and what they do know, as brute beaſts in thoſe things corrupt themſelves, running in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> killing their brethren in the fleſh, becauſe they are not of the ſame judgement and underſtanding in the ſpirit, envying them in the offering of their ſacrifices, becauſe they offer not their ſacrifices as they do: pulling and halling them before Magiſtrates, Counſells, Powers, and Authorities, Impriſoning them, Baniſhing them, confining them, depriving them of their liberties, accounting the world not worthy of them, acou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting them the off ſcouring of all things, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning greedily after the errour of <hi>Baalam</hi> for reward, ſetting ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles in the way of true, reall and unblameable liberty of Saints, in their true and glorious feaſtings of ſpirituall Charity and Love in the diſpenſation of the various gifts of the moſt High God, feeding themſelves without fear, when others are living, walking, talking, lovingly converſing, eating and drinking in fear; Clouds without water, Clouds covering the clear Heavens and Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as if they were full of water, and as if ſhowres would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently fall, great Mountaines travelling in birth, Clouds carried about of winds: from Popery or Popiſh Epiſcopacy to Prelacy in another form, and from that to Presbyterie, and thoſe that would have the ſame wind of Doctrine; the ſame teachings of fallible men to blow others, whetherſoever it blows them, whoſe fruits have often already withered from one age to another, and more then twice dead, and plucked up by the Roots, raging waves of the ſea, foming out their own ſhame, having not the ſpirit of meeknes, gentlenes, tender mercy &amp; compaſſion though Stars, yet wandring Stars, to whom is reſerved blacknes of darknes for ever; and therefore they would draw all men unto them, Murmerers, Complainers, Informers, Reformers according to their own luſts, ſpeaking ſwelling words, having mens perſons in admiration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of advantage (not knowing the glorious minde, infallible will of the eternall God, as the Apoſtles of Ieſus Chriſt) Mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers walking after their own ungodly luſts, ſeperating themſelves by the power, will, minde, fallibility of fallible ſenſuall men, having not the ſpirit, denying any one but themſelves, (and thoſe whom themſelves approve of) to build up any in the holy faith or to Miniſter the gifts they have had of the ſupereminent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94878:17"/> God: Teaching by neceſſarie unavoidable conſequences that their love, ſenſuall, carnall, mutable affections are to be looked after before the love of God; or as well as the love of God (though God the abſolute ſatisfyer, informer, and reformer ſatisfies not.) having no compaſſion but on themſelves &amp; thoſe that they thinke they can by flattery draw to themſelves, making no difference but from themſelves, making no difference according to the true nature of difference, but only making a difference according to their Carnall Lawes, ordinances, Statutes, decrees, not endeavouring to ſave others according to the true abſolute, infallible, holy, juſt, warrantable way of ſalvation, Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to pull men that are (as they ſay erroneous) out of the fire with violence inſtead of feare, malice, hatred, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments, bonds, Endeavouring to pull others out of the fire, and ſave others with a love, reſpect, affection to their fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible mutable garments ſpotted with the fleſh. But oh, immutable, unſpotted, undefiled God! thou who art able to preſent me fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs before the preſence of thy glory with joy, let me not be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from any, or joyned to any when thou ſhalt ſeperate, till thou ſeperateſt and joyneſt; that ſo ſeperation may be of thee, &amp; uniting may be of thee, and that I may hold forth the interior teachings, the hidden unſpeakeable myſterie of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and enjoying. Let me not walke according to the minde and will, of the men of the world, that are ſomething and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that live and command according to the will of the fleſh, let me not walke according to the way of the wandring ſtars, the wonders of the world, of mountains, of Thrones, of Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities and powers of the aire, of the Gods of nations preiſtly Counſels, and Magiſtrates of the earth choſen by men of the earth. But oh Lord! let my Exterior be what the Lord, and not what the Lords will.</p>
            <p>But methought I ſaw the preiſts of the nation in Pompe and glorie, in kings, Monarches and potentates Courts: and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought I ſaw them inſtigating the Civill Magiſtrates of the world, and I ſaw the perſons, and their waies to be the Preiſtly Lineage and the ſucceſſours of the Lord Ieſus, his and his Apoſtles and Saints enemies, who crucified the Lord Jeſus, did kill and ſlay the Apoſtles, and Saints of the moſt high God, and being
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94878:17"/> convinced of the glorie, power, and truth of God, manifeſted in thoſe Apoſtles &amp; Saints, did endeavour to extripate &amp; root them out from off the face of the earth, &amp; made them to wander up &amp; down deſtitute, afflicted, and tormented: And when they thought they had extinguiſhed them, and rooted them out of the world, they ſtiled themſelves the Apoſtles ſucceſſours, Miniſters of the Lord Jeſus, and Prieſts of the high God, like certain of the Jews, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.13. yea Vagabond Jews, Exorciſts, who tooke upon them to call over them that had evill ſpirits, the name of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, whom <hi>Paul</hi> Preached. But here I was caſt into admiration why the world ſhould ever the more admire the Preiſts of nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and their adherent (that are the ſcourgers of Saints, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſers of Magiſtrates) becauſe they pretend to the Lord Jeſus whom <hi>Paul</hi> did enjoy, and whom <hi>Paul</hi> did preach: But preiſts, but Miniſters of the Goſpel as you call your ſelves) though I can ſay in ſome meaſure Ieſus Chriſt! know &amp; ſomewhat by the power of that eternal ſpirit I know, which <hi>Paul</hi> know; But who are ye?</p>
            <p>But though you are in my apprehenſion, the great enemies of the Lord Jeſus, and though I ſhall be accounted an evill ſpirit by you, a Devill, or what not; I would not inſult over you though I had power over you. But it's I can onely ſay, that many of you may be ſaved; it's the eternall, abſolute, and onely wiſe can ſay, you ſhall. But yet I think you ſhall ſuffer the loſſe of your craft; for many perſecutors, both before and in the <hi>Marian</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution became perſecuted ones; the Father called ſome of them from queenly, fleſhly carnall, Antichriſtian glory, to the fire: I deſire, that you would not be offended with words; for I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs ſeriouſly I ſpeak not out of hatred, but out of pitie to you that are in contrarietie to the Lord Jeſus. You often ſay, you acknowledge a God, therefore expect not that I ſhould call you gods that have hands, nor your works gods that are made with hands, nor any or all your minds or underſtandings Gods, even a whole Synod or Counſaile, But the abſolute ſupreame God ſhall be, when you are not to be ſeen; Time may be when your Craft, as well as your predeceſſors craft may be ſet at nought, and your gods and goddeſſes deſpiſed and all your magnificence deſtroyed, though there were as many more, eager and violent perſecutors and worſhippers: are not you the cauſe, whilſt you
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94878:18"/> have the power in your hands, whileſt you have the Kings, Lords, and Potentates of the earth to act for you, that there is ſo great a ſtir about that way which you partiall, fallible Judges call Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: What though you cry out great is <hi>Diana</hi> of the Epheſians? what though you are full of wrath and bitterneſs, ſo that fire proceeds out of your mouth, and as much malice, envy, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velliſh contrariety to all (except your ſelves) as can be ſuppoſed to be in the moſt barbarous and cruell; yet your Kingdom is not an everlaſting Kingdom, nor your Dominion an everlaſting do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, but the ſupream infallible Judge will come gloriouſly, &amp; will not tarry: It is but a <hi>Marian Trick</hi> to perſecute a poor man, and to hale him, or indeavour to bring him before you Commanders in chief; your Magiſtracy and Counſels for Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (as you call it) I will acquaint you with one thing, I provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentially ſaw not long ſince in the Book of Martyrs of one <hi>Raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins White</hi> a Fiſher man of <hi>Cardiff,</hi> who was burnt for an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick: a little before the fire flaſht up to his body, many of his friends came to him and took him by the hand, and one held held him till the flame aroſe and ſeperated friends: but a Prieſt ſaid it was not lawfull to take him by the hand, for he was an Heretick, and condemned by the Church; I wonder Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> doth not inſert this as of divine Authority, to prove the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of perſecution and violence to be uſed to Hereticks.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Nationall Miniſters</hi> you are the Children, or the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Children of thoſe that were ſo conſtituted, and did Act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to an unjuſt papall way, and as one ſayth of them, <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus faetor uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad nubes fumum teterrimum exhalabat,</hi> whoſe filthy ſtinck did fume even to the Clouds of Heaven, but indeed you did ſtill indeavour to cloth your ſelves finer and finer to make the world wonder at you, and think you were really for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, but be not deceived ſo as to think that God can be mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and deluded, though you finde men (almoſt the whole world) very facile and eaſie to be deluded with a lye, with a fancy. It was formerly wont to be ſaid, <hi>Agnus dei qui tollis peccata mundi miſerere nobis,</hi> but muſt we take it in this acceptation, <hi>Synodus Dei qui tollis peccata mundi, miſerere nobis?</hi> Oh the intolerable pride of <hi>Lucifer!</hi> O the Vanity of the high Prieſts! who are made by the power of the great God, to confeſs they are not infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet act as if they were.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:94878:18"/>
            <p>But methinks I ſee and behold (I thank my eternall life and only wiſe God) my Lord to laugh at the Lords, my God at the Gods, the and my abſolute, immutable, perfect, infallible infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and Reformer to laugh at the mutable, non-abſolute, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, fallible Informers, and Reformers; but it may be theſe men may be ſealed up to the judgement of the great Day: but the alone abſolute Judge knowes, and I am alone ſatisfied that he knows, and that he manifeſts, and myſteriouſly containes in his inviſible ſelf what he pleaſeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In my Soliloquies,</hi> in my withdrawings in ſecret before my God (of whom I deſire not to be aſhamed, and unto whom all things are naked and bare) the contrarietie of the powers of the world, made me more now then ever in all my life to look up to God the incomprehenſible glory, to ſee if poſſible I might attain, or had attained to it, as apprehended of him; how I was as to him, which would be the greateſt comfort to me that could bee: if the Lord ſhould lay ſome heavy affliction upon me, if I ſhould be brought before the powers of the world, for I ſaw in the world, and methinks I ſee and hear the Crowned Beaſts (as well as the Saints of the moſt High, the fellowſhip of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the ſon of God that are round about the Throne) cry Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Holy, Holy, Lord God Almighty, which was and is, and is to come, I ſaw the whole World in confuſion, and yet walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their place; the beaſts in their place of adoration, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the moſt high God under the ſame forms of expreſſion or Miniſtration of holineſs and glory, that the Saints of the moſt High did. But I ſee &amp; underſtand a variety of manifeſtation of the great God of Heaven and earth in diſtinction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But I</hi> ſeeing and beholding the Beaſts of the earth to have a Crown, power, and authority given them to kill with the ſword, under the name of the worſhip, ſervice, glory, and excellency of the moſt High God, and it made me that have lived (in the time of my ignorance of God, or life to God with God) after the fleſh, deceit, formall man, teachings, and fallible apprehenſions to look and ſee, if I could behold, or attain to ſee the eternal, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute &amp; infallible to comprehend me in the body of the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus &amp; to ſee if I lived to the life ſuperemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to the life ſuſtaining, feeding, even to the abſolute, true, and not fading principle of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94878:19"/> glory, and to ſee if I lived to the true beams, life and Communion of true underſtanding. <hi>But Lords, Counſels, Synods,</hi> or Honourable men, of good, &amp; admired literature, you that deſire to be reformers of men for the ſalvation of ſouls, you that conceive your ſelves to be the men abſolutely infallible in your ſelves, &amp; undeniable to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers called of God more then the generation of preiſts, or Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods before you, you that ſo well conceive of your ſelves that you act not from Preiſtly Marian principles, as the Preiſts, your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors did, you alſo that hold foorth your doctrine, as they did theirs, from your owne or your Fathers interpretation of Scriptures, you that endeavour to limit and binde in Chaynes of darkeneſſe and ſelfe, you that would have none teach but your ſelves, or rather to miniſter what they apprehend of God, but your ſelves as your Fathers before you. I deſire you and earneſtly intreate you, as you tender the Scriptures of God which you (as if convincedly, truly, and knowingly maintaine and preach from) And becauſe it may not be ſaid if you, (if it be not true of you) according to that Rule of imperiouſneſs earthlineſs, ſenſuality, and Deviliſhneſs, wiſdom (and yet folly) <hi>Sic volo ſic jubeo, ſtat pro ratione Voluntas;</hi> And furthermore becauſe it is ſaid in the 5 <hi>Iames</hi> 20. let him know that he which converteth a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from the errour of his way, ſhall ſave a ſoule from death, and ſhall hide a multitude of ſinnes, (if you infallibly know, as many of you ſeeme conſtantly to averr, that this Scripture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs unto you, to make uſe of) Conſider you are men, and not God. You are many men, and you have many minds, See and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold (if you can) whether you may not be condemned by the Eternall God, though you condemne not your ſelves, or judge your ſelves; if you are now of one minde in your Aſſembly, you are not to be conſidered eternaly ſo; for yeſterday you were of one mind, to day, you are of another, &amp; before many daies or yeares come to be conſummated by that eternall God, (who is uncapable of change) you may be of another minde, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to them both; you have hiſſed at the generations; that have been paſt, &amp; at the generation that is, but the generations that are to come may hiſs at you, and may be aſhamed of their fathers pretended infallibilities; you or your fathers have Clipt the wings, whipt, ſcourged, impriſoned the bodies, in fine abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94878:19"/> thoſe that have been contrary to you; what did you do as you would be done by? Did not many of you that pretend to have a holy reſpect to the Sabbath, read (your ſelves, or countenance the reading in others) the book of ſports. And will you now make it your ſport to perſecute? Did you not live farr below the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly glory of knowing, and underſtanding? How will it be with you, when God ſhall ſay to your Conſciences, you that thought you knew ſo much of me, did not know your ſelves; you that were ready, and violently ready to ſcourge, had need be ſcourged, even at the ſame time, of God. It is true, I gave you underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, power, and Crownes on your heads, and I will judge you according to what you are, and with what you have, as I have your fathers before you. Time was, when you would take notice of none crowned but your ſelves, none honoured of God but your ſelves, as if you comprehended all the incommunicable and communicable varieties of my ſelfe, as if you had the infallible diſcerning of ſpirits, but now I will ſhew thee thoſe whom thou perſecutedſt, thoſe whom thou eſteemedſt the off-ſcouring of all things, the filth of the whole world, to weare Crowns of gold, and white Rayment, though you had Crowns, though powers, kingdomes, &amp; glories, though you are diſputing, intellectuall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and have rationall capacities, though governours of multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, Nations, Kindreds, and tongues, yet you have not white Garments before the All-ſeeing, Supereminent, eternall <hi>Iehovah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When you Lords of earth ſhall ſee one that you Lorded over, crowned with tranſparent gold, Crowned with the tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent power, life, wiſdome, and love of the eternall, inviſible God, and in the body of Jeſus Chriſt, if you ſhall behold it in time, Oh then my Lords, <hi>Tempora mutantur;</hi> if when time ſhall be no more, what ſhall my Lords be, I ſhall expatiate my ſelfe accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scriptures of God. 10 <hi>Luke.</hi> Chriſt gave power to (and manifeſted the fathers glory in) a few poore diſciples, a few tormented, hated, perſecuted Saints; to caſt out Devills, to tread upon <hi>Scorpions,</hi> and all the power of the Enemy; But ſurely they became not a Magiſtraticall power, to accompliſh ſuch a Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and though he gave them ſuch power, he told them, there was no cauſe of triumph in this, or joy in this, that the ſpirits were ſubject unto them, but rather that their names were written in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94878:20"/> heaven, what though their are many ſpirits gone abroad in the world, Sectaries, the divills of the world, (as you call them) your rejoycing would be rather (if you had ſuch a glorious Apoſtolic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Commiſſion power &amp; glory) that your names were writen in heaven, that you your ſelves are comprehended in the boſome of the Father: But yet if you did ſo your ſelves, and know your ſelves, it would be queſtionable whether you have this Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call power and glory, if not the one, ſurely not the other. But you may have a Crown, power, and authority continued to you, to ſcourge and crucifie.</p>
            <p>It it is ſaid in the 21. and 22 verſes, The eternall ſupereminent, the Lord of Heaven and earth, had hid wiſdome from the wiſe and prudent, and revealed it to babes: Lords tell the people playnly and diſtinctly, whether you can ſay that it ſeemed good in the ſight of the Lord to alter his viſible diſpenſations, and to reveal his truth to Lords, Potentates, Counſelours, wiſe men, prudent men, Sattin men, Purple and Diamond men (that is to ſay) thoſe that go in gay cloathing, and would ſway the whole world, thoſe that have reſpect of perſons, thoſe that muſt ſit here, and ſit there, becauſe they are thus, and thus: Chriſt told his diſciples that many prophets &amp; Kings, did deſire to ſee the things that they ſaw and did not ſee them, and to hear the things that they had heard, and did not hear them. But admit there have been prophets, Kings, and Lords, ſince that, which have ſeene the things of God, you may not be ſuch men, that are now in this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, Chriſt ſaid all the glories of the Father were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him, and that no man did know who the Sonne is, but the father; and who the father is, but the ſon, and he to whom the ſonne will reveale him, even that ſonne who hath power over all fleſh to give eternall life to as many as the father pleaſeth. But Lords, Synods, Counſailes, can you ſay all things are delivered unto you of the father? though you have Crownes, though you have power, yet have a power of mutability your power is not that power of all: that power of love, of life, of perfection, of infalliblity: do you know the ſonne as well as the Father, and the father as well as the ſonne? Doe you know how many? and who, if how many, the father will give eternall life unto, by Ieſus Chriſt? do you perſecute (you being fallible ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94878:20"/> to your owne confeſſion) becauſe you would bring into the fold thoſe that are not yet brought in, but muſt be, or would you be certain, infallible, powerfull aſſiſtants with Ieſus Chriſt, the abſolute Lord, or do you intend to perſecute thoſe that are not intended according to an eternall intendment, to be of the body of Jeſus Chriſt? if ſo, are you as certain, as Chriſt is certain, that this is the Harveſt? and are you as certain that you are the reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? that you your ſelves are not the tares? are you the Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, yea the ten Thouſands of Saints by which he will come to judge the world? Hath the Father altered his mind in relation to manifeſtation, and told you that you muſt pluck up the tares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Harveſt? Or was not that his minde, when he declared that the tares ſhould grow together till the Harveſt? Hath the Father or hath the Son revealed theſe things unto you in this generation? if ſo tell us; and when it was; and how: and it will be a greater glory unto you, then to ſit a great while &amp; bring out a few fallible contrivances, &amp; Scholaſtick inventions. But it is far more glorious, and a greater matter of rejoycing to you to be lead (if leade) then to leade, for the all-ſufficient immutable Lord to leade the lords, the people and Nations, then for blind lords and Prieſts to leade poor blind people.</p>
            <p>How would the ſupereminent be exalted here? Admit that the Sectaries of the times, thoſe that are called Divels incarnat (by you Potentates of the world) ſhould in their journey to or from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> fall amongſt theeves, and ſhould be ſtripped of their rayment and be wounded; ſhould yield to the temptations of that raging divell in the world, in and ſince the Apoſtacy, or ſince that Satans Mineſtery &amp; Magiſtracy hath had and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their power in the world. Is it commendable in the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> to ſee them ſo, and to paſs by on the other ſide? or is it commendable for theſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> to add, or cauſe others to add afflictions to their bonds: But theſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> God will not honour ſo much. The <hi>Samaritan</hi> muſt come and ſee alſo, and have compaſſion. <hi>Oh Good Samaritan!</hi> for the poor, wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſtripped, and torn man; this is an excellent ſimilitude, the ſupereminentneſs, and gloriouſneſs conſiſts in the ſubſiſtance.</p>
            <p>But Oh! unmercifull High Prieſts and <hi>Levites,</hi> when God hath ſent a meſſenger of <hi>Satan,</hi> to buffet a man and to have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94878:21"/> power over the bodie, &amp; may be the underſtanding in temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will you buffett and impriſon much more: looke to your commiſſion, may not God ſay to a Synod in this caſe as Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> in another <hi>Get thee behinde me Satan,</hi> Are you better then <hi>Peter</hi> was? if you are, or if you thinke you are, dare not Chriſt ſay ſo as well to a Synod as to a <hi>Peter?</hi> But this is your pity, if wee were wounded and naked, and if you were (as you are not) the true, loving, compaſſionate, judging, diſcerning perſons, I think you had need to have the moſt glorious, infallible Commiſſion for your ſecurity that may bee, ſo to perſecute and proſecute, if it were lawfull ſo to doe. What cruelty is it in you who made not your ſelves, to deſtroy your ſelves? you that are not able to make a man to deſtroy a man, ſtarve a man for that which is in the conſcience, even for that which a man himſelfe is not Lord of, when you nor he are truly able to add one Cubit to his ſtature, unleſſe that you goe to a Shoomaker for a paire of Heeles. Indeed what ye make you may marre, but 11 <hi>Luke</hi> 40. Ye fooles, did not hee that made that which is without, make that which is within alſo, <hi>Profecto teſtificamini quod conſentitis, operibus patrum Veſtorum;</hi> For ought you know, God hath ſent a few mechanicall illiterate fellowes (as you call them,) that the bloud and cruelty of all Generations may be ſet on the ſcore of the continued ſucceſſiue perſecutors as wel as upon thoſe who ſlew and dealt injuriouſly with the Prophets and Apoſtles. But this will not excuſe you, to ſay you had power to binde heavy burthens on others ſhoulders, and not to touch them your ſelves with one of your fingers; This will not exuſe you before the Supereminent life glory, Lord abſolute, diſcerne judge to ſay; what tongue, or Lord ſhall controul us? Surely I think if Chriſt Ieſus the head, the anoynted, of God in peculiarity, were in the world now, as he was, in ſo deſpicable manner to his enemies, you would ſcarce afford him to write, or ſeeme to write upon the ground, If he did we ſhould have a <hi>gangraena</hi> made preſently to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn this <hi>Heretick,</hi> this <hi>Belzebub,</hi> this friend to <hi>publicans</hi> &amp; <hi>ſinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Lords, But Counſailes but Synods, in fine but men, when the abſolute Lord,</hi> and ſupereminent God ſhal tell you (though a poore man) it may be that is iudged and condemned before you may not neither doth that you who were, or are, called Lords in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94878:21"/> the ſublunary, Viſible Kingdome &amp; glory did endeavour to caſt a moate out of anothers eye, &amp; you had a beame in your owne, and that you having a beam are no competent judges of a mote.</p>
            <p>But it may be you will ſay that you are infallible in this, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſay, that that ſaying of Chriſt doth not appertain to you; <hi>Let him that is without ſin caſt the firſt ſtone,</hi> when God ſhall diſcover himſelf and manifeſt you what you are, even that you that judge other, are Caſt-awaies your ſelves, are Hereticks your ſelves, you would not be very willing to finde a ſtone for another. When the Lord ſhall ſay though you cried <hi>Templum Domini, Templum Domini,</hi> yet the everlaſting was not in your eſteem, even he that can when he will both caſt out Beam and Mote. But thus it is, when the Lord is not or will not be underſtandingly &amp; ſuperemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently in the Lords thoughts, though he be neer and ſees, yet he will not be ſeen; but they ſay, how doth God know? can he judge through the dark Cloud, thick Clouds are a covering to him that he ſeeth not, and he walketh in the circuit of heaven, <hi>Job</hi> 22, 23, 24. <hi>But Oh Immortality!</hi> thy righteouſneſs, thy ſeeing, and thy ſeeing to be ſeen, thy knowing to be known, and thy under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to be underſtood ſhines not upon all. Thou haſt O Lord ſet the world in my heart, ſo that no man can finde out the work that thou haſt made from the beginning to the end. <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes</hi> 3.11. Therefore Lord if thou wilt give a Crown, Power, and Authority to Temporarie Lords to excerciſe their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and power even upon me, if thou ſhalt manifeſt me and make me a little flame of thy ſelf, thy will be done. It is only in thy ſelf to comprehend the works that thou haſt made from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to the end, if man indeavours to comprehend, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to inthrone himſelf in a ſtate of comprehending others, and perſecuting others from an apprehenſion that he comprehends, when he doth not in deed and in truth: and though I ſhall (if thou comprehending incomprehenſib e, willeſt) be afflicted, ſcorrned, &amp; contemned by that generation; yet let me in particular lie down and be ſatisfied, that I am apprehended and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended of thee, and that I know, ſee, and ſpeake, according to the true and reall nature of knowing, ſeeing, &amp; ſpeaking, &amp; living, and injoying, as comprehended: let me ſee, before I ſay I ſee, know, before I ſay I know, and be ſpoken to, before I ſpeak:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94878:22"/> Oh! thou immutable knower, ſee'r, and abſolute ſpeaker, as to the things that thou haſt made capable of ſeeing, knowing, and ſpeaking, let thy loving ſpirit of righteouſneſs and wiſdom up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me; and though thou delivereſt me to the ungodly, and turneſt me over into the hands of the wicked, let me ſay truly, knowingly, and underſtandingly; my witneſs is in heaven, and my record is on high, in love, <hi>Job</hi> 26.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Counſellours</hi> of the Earth, <hi>Weak Contenders</hi> of the Earth with the abſolute Lord: I ſee and conſider oppreſſions (though I ſee not all oppreſſions) under the Sun. But a comfort it is that the abſolute Lord ſees, <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 4.1, 2. But it may be Lords, you will ſay when you perſecute, there is no remedy in the death of a man, it is ſutable to conveniency, and the conſtitution of a Kingdom to deſtroy a man: ſo as it was indeed to crucifie the Son of God, who was known, &amp; is known to ſome, not to be held of the grave: But you it may be, will ſay you have not known any man to returne; it may be you will ſay men are born at an adventure, and ſhall be hereafter as though they had never bin; &amp; that the breath of your noſtrils is as ſmoake, a little ſpark in the moving of your Breaſt; which being extinguiſhed, your body ſhall be turned into aſhes, and your ſpirit ſhall vaniſh as the ſoft Aire, therefore you will lie in waite for the righteous, becauſe he is not for your turn, he is clean contrary to your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, becauſe he profeſſeth to have the knowledge of God, and he calleth himſelf the child of the Lord, he is made to reprove your doings, therefore he is grievous to behold, becauſe his life is not like other mens, his waies are of another faſhion, becauſe you are eſteemed of him as counterfeits, and he abſtaineth from your filthineſs, and becauſe he maketh his boaſt that God is his Father. And therefore you will examine him with deſpightful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and torture, to know his meekneſs, and prove his Patience. But <hi>Potentates,</hi> I ſhall preſent a few things to your conſideration, paradventure you may ſee with your eyes and heare with your ears, and when you are converted (if ever you ſhall) you may ſet to your ſeals that theſe things are true; to the praiſe and glory of the abſolute,, infallible God, Judge, power, wiſdome, and true glory.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God is the alone ſupream, King of kings, Lord of lords,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94878:22"/> and God may, as well as he hath already, give the Nations, (or thoſe to whom he intends, to ſhew and manifeſt himſelf unto) a light and glorious underſtanding, to ſee that Lords (by ſpeciall authority and power formerly conſtituted) are but types and ſhadowes of the abſolute ſupream, immortall God and Judge: but this is true, though the Lords and Kings ſee it not themſelves, for I know they will ſay, you Prophecie not good unto them in theſe things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt the perfect pattern of the Fathers, manifeſted perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to men; never gave any ſuch power or kingly authority to any that then were in the world, either Magiſtrates or Apoſtles; he never gave the Apoſtles power to exerciſe themſelves with ſcourgings, whippings, impriſonments, baniſhments, or oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſuch a kind, therefore there is no ſuch ſucceſſive Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3, 4. verſes <hi>If he that cometh, Preacheth another Jeſus whom we have not Preached, and if ye receive another Spirit whom ye have not received, or another Goſpel which ye have not accepted, ye might well bear with him.</hi> Likewiſe there was power given, or the manifeſtation of the moſt High in a way ſupereminent, that the Saints ſhould do great things by the power of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and in the name of the Lord Jeſus, that ſupereminent name, that name above every name. <hi>In whoſe name the ſeventy return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with joy, and ſaid, the Devils were ſubject unto them by it.</hi> Luke 10.17. I know no other authority, power, or glory given to any that ſhould profeſs that name according to the ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſts commanding the Apoſtles to give <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due, and God his due, is a plain demonſtration, that ſomewhat might be due to the one that was not due to the other: and if the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate would demand Lordſhip over the body and conſcience, what would they leave for God, the eternall, infallible Ruler? Or doth the ſoul, the underſtanding alone belong to God, and the body belong to man, in relation to the commands of the Divine God?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Externall contrariety to Magiſtracy is apparant by Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles in their Preachings of the truth, and way of the moſt High God; ſo that as the viſible doth do what he is commanded by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> If that inviſible God command an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other thing in the conſcience or underſtanding; for Chriſt was
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94878:23"/> not contrary in the inviſibility, but alſo contrary in the viſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to the <hi>Magiſtracy, Governours, High-Prieſts, Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees.</hi> Chriſt never inſlaved himſelf, nor the minde of his Apoſtles to the Magiſtrates and powers of the earth. And there can be no more Conformity demanded from any, to any Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, but only what he obeyed, and taught others to obey, even in the paying of Tribute to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Or unleſs a man be taught (by that Miniſtring ſpirit which was promiſed to direct into truth) to be obedient to a Magiſtracy in ſome other things which Chriſt was not obedient in; or was to be ſubject unto: no power of conſcience to Magiſtracy. Again, the children will not be free in the Magiſtrates jurisdiction from paying of Tribute, ſo long as they have that benefit to live in the world amongſt them, in buying and ſelling. God will not have his Saints to appear more glued to the world then other men; to get by the world, and not to let the world have a benefit from them as well as ſtrangers or other Cohabiters: and indeed it is good for the maintayning of love and Unity in the world, and that which doth compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend in it a poſſibility to live peaceably with all men. And a Magiſtrate (if he be one that walketh and judgeth according to the pure light of nature and right reaſon) is to ſee that there be no injury offered to peaceable men amongſt them: and for this cauſe, the Saints or thoſe of contrary judgements pay Tribute alſo, becauſe they are or ſhould be the Miniſters of God attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon this thing. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.6. And therefore very conſcionable that they ſhould have Tribute, whether they are appointed of God in an immediate manner, or of men in a mediate; if they are (as they are not) appointed of God in an immediate, in a more eſpeciall (if God ſhall ſend ſuch, or conſtitute ſuch a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy) then reaſon to pay Tribute, if appointed of men in a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate, good reaſon alſo becauſe the people, multitudes or Nations, have made choice of ſome to do their buſineſs, to be their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and ſo long as the children of the Kingdom of God, have their juſt, lawfull, and naturall liberties, and freedomes, to act in their ſeverall trades and occupations in the world, in godlineſs and honeſty, they will yield to <hi>Caeſar</hi> in thoſe things which a Law of nature or of conveniency obligeth them to, if they were not commanded: for if they live quietly under a Magiſtracy in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94878:23"/> or according to the teaching and way of the moſt High God in a way of peculiarity; then they alſo exerciſe themſelves in honeſty, in relation to civils or to Magiſtracy. No power of conſcience given to Magiſtracy.</p>
            <p>But if they are deprived of the ſupreme and abſolute Glory of manifeſtation of themſelves, as to God, even in godlineſs <hi>(viz)</hi> by impriſonment, baniſhment, or by confiſcation of goods, or their converſing with men becauſe they will not receive the marke of the beaſt, then the Magiſtracy weaken their owne, and the Kingdomes ſtrength. But yet they fulfill their owne wills on them, but indeed have no dominion ouer the Saints at all.</p>
            <p>But if it be the Fathers pleaſure, the Saints may live under a <hi>Caeſar,</hi> a <hi>Caligula,</hi> a <hi>Nero,</hi> a <hi>Domitian,</hi> or another ſucceſſive civill Magiſtracy in theſe conſiderations, peaceably and quietly in all godlineſs and honeſty (not affording a power of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence at all) though they are perſecuted and afflicted, deſpiſed, ſcorned and oppreſſed, and ſo not live quietly, and peaceably, yet they may live godlily, and honeſtly amongſt them, or in the Nation under the power of a Magiſtracy and the Apoſtle might pray for it to the Father, and yet magiſtracy have no power of conſcience; again though they are perſecuted and afflicted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Civill Magiſtracy, and ſo not live quietly and peaceably as before, yet they themſelves may live quietly, and peaceably in Godlineſs, and honeſty <hi>(viz)</hi> they may not be diſturbers, though they are diſturbed; afflictors and ſcourgers, though ſcourged; Tormentors, though Tormented; buffetters, though buffetted: in fine, may not walke contrary to the pure light of nature, and right reaſon, though others doe ſo to them, and ſo they may live quietly, peaceably, godlily, and honeſtly in the midſt of a perverſe, irrationall, ſelf-iſh generation; and ſo they may pray the Father to live, though they give no power of conſcience to magiſtracy. And therefore a poore diſpiſed Apoſtle being ready to be devoured by every one, to be ſpitt on by every one, in his abundant labours, in his ſtripes above meaſure, in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons frequent, being beaten with rods, being ſtoned, being in perills of waters, in perills of robbers, in perills by his owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, in perills by the heathen, in perills by the City, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ills in the wilderneſs, in perills amongſt falſe brethren, might
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94878:24"/> very well breake out and pray to the eternall God to alter and change the powers of the world, if that eternall God would that he or the poore Saints might live a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty: ſhall an Apoſtle ſpeake of the things of his Father, and for it be ready to be devoured, and ſhall a Magiſtrate countenance it? ſhall he have ſtripes by authority, and without authority, be beaten with Rods, be impriſoned, be in perill of robbers, in the City, in the Wilderneſs? What is a Magiſtrate for then?</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle being under ſo great preſſures, in relation to the walking of Magiſtracy contrary to the pure light of nature and right reaſon, might well become a ſuiter to the Father, for a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of quietneſs and peace under Magiſtracy. But yet Oh Lord abſolute and undefiled, though thou giveſt a crown to defiled Magiſtracy to take peace from the earth, thy alone eternall will be accompliſhed and performed, and let thy Saints live to thee, the ſupream Magiſtiſtrate power, and authority, if thou wilt not ſuffer them to live quietly and peaceably in the jurisdiction of the powers of the world.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Though the Magiſtrates may command the body, yet they are only to command as I ſaid before, that which a Saint would willingly do for peace and quietneſs ſake, if he were only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, or neither commanded or intreated; ſo that he will act being commanded, and act being intreated, and alſo though nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commanded nor intreated. But when the body was to be with Jeſus Chriſt, who was manifeſted in the fleſh, or when the body is exerciſed according to the life, power, and will of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Lord, in Communion with thoſe that have the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the moſt high, in knowing and underſtanding, then the Saints muſt not feare them that can kill the body, <hi>(viz)</hi> magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, but they muſt walk as the divine, ſupereminent Saviour, Lord, King Judge wil have them. Suppoſe that a Magiſtrate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands my body to do one thing, but the inviſible God in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, he that is God of body and ſoule commands ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing; whether is it lawfull to obey God or man? Judge ye.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Suppoſe there is ſuch a Magiſtrate in the world that does truely and really conceive that there is one eternall God, the judge, the abſolute God, the Lawgiver in the conſcience, and he
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94878:24"/> according to rationality doth endeavour to demonſtrate it, can he make another beleeve it? &amp; if any conforme to what he ſaieth, not knowing it, is not he, an ignorant doer of what he would have him to do, or a diſſembling perſon? But <hi>Aug.</hi> one of <hi>Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graena's</hi> Fathers ſaith, <hi>Simulata ſanctitas eſt duplex iniquitas.</hi> But the Magiſtrates, and Prieſts of the earth, have led the world in a ſtring, and they are at the ſenſuall beck, and will of every baſe luſt, and that rule is verified amongſt them <hi>qui neſcit diſſimulare neſcit vivere,</hi> But Oh! how excellent will it be when Saints ſhall more and more live to the ſupreame abſolute God!</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether a man may not have a word of God to deliver to a Magiſtrate, as well as a Magiſtrate to another man? Former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I know God called ſome to ſpeake to Kings, and Potentates of the earth. But we are better then our Fathers. Is not the ſpirit of forbearance as good in a Magiſtrate as it is in another man? if the Magiſtrate hath had experience that no man can make him beleeve the truths of God, &amp; that he can not make any one; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe why ſhould he uſe violence, bitterneſs, and wrath? But we call it not wrath, we call it Juſtice.</p>
            <p>But the abſolute diſtinguiſher ſees what it is, and he will call that wrath and anger in you, which you call juſtice. But we will contrive a great many fine words to waue it. But there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hath power, but what is given to it, nothing enjoyes it longer, then he that gave it, pleaſeth; neither ſhall any thing be waved, but what he will wave, even that abſolute, I am: But oh! Lord ſupereminent, if thou calleſt me, cauſeſt me to ſpeak of thee, to manifeſt thee, though magiſtracy heape up words againſt me, &amp; ſtrengthen their mouthes, according to the judgement of Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidicks &amp; Synods of the earth, though they hale me, &amp; teare me in their ire, &amp; ſharpen their eys at me, yet let it be ſufficient that thou loveſt, &amp; when ſoever I ſee man, let me be drawn to God, &amp; let me ſay with <hi>Iob</hi> in the ſpirit of underſtanding without reſpect of perſons. <hi>Iob</hi> 20.4, 5, 6, 7. Knoweſt thou not this of old ſince man was placed upon the earth, that the triumph of the wicked is ſhort, and the joy of the wicked is but for a moment? Though his Excellencie mount up to the heavens, and his head reach to the clouds, yet he ſhall periſh for ever like his owne dung, they which have ſeen him ſhall ſay where is he?</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:94878:25"/>8. Thoſe that the Magiſtrates endeavour to compell to the Laws, wills, Ordinances, interpretations of Scriptures (the Magiſtrates being and confeſſing themſelves fallible) may, for ought the Magiſtrates know, have an obligation and an abſolute underſtanding, ingagement upon their ſpirits as to God, to live to Gods owne interpretation, Law, will, and ordinance; which may be contrary to the Magiſtrate. For God is the abſolute ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of all things that are, and that are to be interpreted.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The People ſhall not ſuffer for the Magiſtrates ſins, but their owne, nor the Magiſtrates, for the peoples ſins, but their owne. But the ſoule that ſinneth ſhall die: But yet in a common calamity the one may ſuffer as well as the other, though not for the ſins of another, 18 <hi>Eezekiel,</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4. &amp;c. There is a declaration as from the Lord. <hi>And the word of the Lord came to me ſaying,</hi> What meane ye that ye Uſe this Proverb, concerning the Land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaying, the Fathers have eaten ſower Grapes, and the childrens Teeth are ſet on edge? <hi>As I live ſaith the Lord, ye ſhall not have occaſion any more to uſe this Proverb in Iſrael.</hi> Behold all ſouls are mine, as the ſoule of the Father, ſo alſo the ſoule of the ſonne is mine; The ſoule that ſinneth, it ſhall die: you may reade the whole Chapter. This was a glorious Propheſie, of the time that ſhould be, when God ſhould peculiarly manifeſt himſelfe, when God would be no more vayled by a man, when God would manifeſt himſelfe to be the abſolute Lord, me thinks a Magiſtrate (confeſſing himſelfe fallible) ſhould feare to deſire, much more to command another, to that which that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not ſatisfied of God. For the ſoule of the perſon that the Magiſtrate commands, is Gods. It was no argument, for a poor ſoule, when the abſolute ſupreame entred into judgement, to ſay that the Magiſtrate gave me and I did eate, nor an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Magiſtrate to ſay, that a companie of people in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted me with this, and that authority, (as I thought) or deſired this, or that thing, and I did eate: I had received a Petition from the people, or from the Major part to releaſe one <hi>Barabbas,</hi> &amp; crucifie Jeſus Chriſt, I received a Petition to deprive ſuch and ſuch People of their liberties, (being ſuch as they, when they did petition, confeſſed God had honoured in doing them good) eſtates, priviledges, and benefits of living in the world, unleſſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94878:25"/> they indeed, were not perſwaded of in their own conſciences. If it was an Argument inexcuſable that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> uſed to God, this may alſo hardly be. They had an infallible Miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what ſhould be death and life: But the Magiſtracy of the world, and Synods of the times (confeſs themſelves fallible) It was an Argument in that moſt certain caſe for <hi>Satan</hi> to uſe, to ſuggeſt to poor weak <hi>Eve,</hi> as it was preſented to deceive: God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, your eys ſhall be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and ye ſhall be as gods, knowing good and evil. But oh Lord I let me ſeek unto thee, with thee, and from thee, though that Devil tempts me to unite, and manifeſt my ſelf to that, and in that way of darkneſs, and man-ſinning in the world, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſpecious, and fallacious pretences, I ſhall receive from the men of the world, and from my own ſoul, as conſidered in its way of operations contrary to the body of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Let me, though I hear men in the world pretend to the glorious my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Eternall God, and the honour and glory of him, try things with thy ſelf alone; and therefore, be thou pleaſed to condeſcend to be my Companion, and teach me the way of thy Commandments in the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Though honour, pleaſure, and preferment is preſented to me, if I ſubmit to that way that I am, or am not perſwaded is the way of God, as conſidered in diſtinction in thy production in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Let me hate (O ſtrength) all objects that are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with pleaſantneſs to my eyes, and with affection to my underſtanding, though it be preſented unto me, to be deſired, and to make me wiſe: If thou doſt contradict all thoſe exterior preſentations in the Interioreſt, And let me not value the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, credit, reſpect, and reputation of men of the world but be thou my God, and then I ſhall have rejoycing, though I ſhall be caſt out of the Paradice of men, and kept out every way with a flaming ſword: But in this my affliction let me have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and power with thy ſelf, or elſe I ſhall prove a Devil to my ſelf, and preſent the glories of the world to my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſhall be deceived.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, Admit that the Laws, Ordinances of man, or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations of Scriptures by man were plain; muſt not God, the abſolute, and infallible, and Supream power, accompliſh in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94878:26"/> the hearts and ſpirits of all men, a beleeving of plain things as well as myſterious things (that have more palpable neceſsity to have the truth, and pure minde of them declared.) The Spirit was promiſed to ſhew the Saints plainly of the Father: If the Father intended we ſhould have Lords of the earth to ſhew us plainly of the Father, and to make us beleeve the plainneſs of the Supereminent teachings, ſurely he would have told us that the Fathers ſhall teach us; The LORDS ſhall inſtruct us: The variable, mutable, fallible, windy ſpirits ſhall teach us.</p>
            <p>But if we are ſubject to ſuch teachings: The fallible, mutable, ſpiritual men, or ſpirits of the world, may caſt out Devils in the name of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and ſweep, and garniſh the houſe, that ſeven other Devils far worſe then the former may enter in.</p>
            <p>Eleaventh, Admit magiſtrates, and natural high Prieſts were the ſervants of the moſt high God, the beloved of the Father, thoſe that knew the myſteries of the Lord Jeſus, were infallible in all knowledge, or if they were true and reall Faſters, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſons; have they any other way preſcribed to caſt out Devils out of thoſe that are in their eyes damnable Hereticks, ſuch as are really poſſeſſed with the ſpirit of blaſphemy, then by Faſting and Prayer? Have they any ſuch rule as this, by ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, by whippings, by impriſonments, by baniſhments? Howbeit, ſaith Chriſt, this kinde cometh not out but by faſting and Prayer, and no more. There is no other way ſpoken of by Chriſt, but by faſting from ſelf, from ſtrife, and from debate, and from ſtriking with the fiſt of wickedneſs, living to, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the will of the Supereminent in faſting, in willing, in deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, according to the effluxes, and deſcendings of it to capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: ſo that then faſting is good, and praying is exceeding good, when the wil of the Supereminent &amp; everlaſting is become mans wil, or mans will become the wil of the ſupereminent, ſubſtantial, eternal, undefiled God, which ſhal certainly be accompliſhed. But if even their very Faſting and praying (according to the true, and real nature of Faſting and praying) be queſtionable, whither will they flie for their actions of Perſecution and Tyrannie?</p>
            <p>Twelfth, Admit the generallity, or major part of Civill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy were truly godly, and heavenly-minded (though I muſt confeſs I know no ſuch matter, it is well for themſelves, if they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94878:26"/> truly know themſelves ſo) and did walk in the Spirit; would they not ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> did, concerning his brethren after the fleſh, who was ſo taken up with love to them, that he would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed from <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> for his brethren after the fleſh (who no doubt had errours, yet not perſecuted by him) would they not ſay, ſurely theſe are men as well as our ſelves, and we cannot chooſe but confeſs our ſelves fallible; we have not the Superemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent light, and perfection of infallibility diſcovered to us, as we confeſs the Apoſtles had; we have not the infallible minde of God diſcovered to us without the Scriptures; we have not the infallibility of interpretation of the minde of God in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; theſe men that we now Perſecute, though as now after the fleſh to us, may be in relation to God the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> according to Faith; unto theſe may belong the Promiſes, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, the giving of the Law of the moſt high God and LORD in Tables of the heart, as well within as without, as well within in love, as within in terrour. We have had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in this particular already; that thoſe that have been extream vitious, are become Religious; we our ſelves have been debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, moſt deſperate ſwearers and blaſphemers of that Eternall being, (and are ſo ſtill) and we ſaw (or many of us) that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing did us good truly, but the light and love of the abſolute, Divine, Supereminent: Truly all are dry-vines, there is but one Supereminent power: Why ſhould any the Dry-vines of the world urge ſuch a thing on us, as to lift us up, and inſtigate us to Perſecute a company of poor, may be, afflicted, tormented, tempted creatures of God, as well as our ſelves, if they have received the Spirit of the Lord? So ſaid their fathers before them, and yet Perſecuted the members of Chriſt; they may boaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their line, as well as others have: If they have the Spirit, they have received it, why ſhould they boaſt? Why ſhould they inſult, domineer, and Tyrannize over others?</p>
            <p>Suppoſe Lords of the Earth, that ſome of you ſhould give a gift to ſome one man, and not to another, or a better gift to one man then to another, as a badge of your mutable honour and love, ſhould another now that meets with one that hath not this badge, rend him and tear him for it? if that he did alſo meet one that had not ſo excellent a badge of honour as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94878:27"/> ſhould he alſo impriſon him, and wound him, or ſtrip him naked? Surely I ſhould think its becauſe he is ſo covetous, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the garment: The Prieſt and the Levite that came by the poor Samaritane, might be the Theeves: Apply it Potentates.</p>
            <p>Beſides, admit you ſhould give a man an excellent badge, or cognizance of love in your families, you ſhould array him in glorious apparell, and ſet a crown of gold on his head, would you take it well, that he ſhould beat his fellow ſervants, and wound them? Reflect my Lords, that he ſhould kill all other poor creatures, that came in his way, becauſe they had not the like garbe; truly, you would ſay this with your ſelf; I may give my own to whom I will; ſo long as I have, I may give what I have; he hath abuſed my love and favour towards him. It may be you may judge your ſelves for your liberality; but Gods ways are paſt finding out; and God may give forth ſome way or other to diſcover the thoughts of all hearts. Oh Lord Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminent! Thou haſt made all men almoſt to differ one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and thou haſt ſet the world in their hearts: to ſome thou didſt give the gift of propheſie (it may be) in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to ſome Tongues, to ſome diſcerning of ſpirits, to ſome work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of miracles, to ſome wiſdom, to ſome knowledge, to ſome Faith; if thou giveſt me but the glimmerings of love in the leaſt of theſe, or in any one, let me not deſpiſe him that hath more, or judge him that hath more, nor yet deſpiſe him that hath leſs, or judge him that hath leſs (if any have leſs then my ſelf) in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to capacity, or underſtanding, for thou art the ſame; let me not prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to know above what I really know, though the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the world would have me do that I am not convinced of; or leave undone, that which I cannot, becauſe I am thine, not their ſervant: Oh then the abſolute Lord, over-rule the lords in me, and let me ſee thee, and walk before thee in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: yet if thou wilt have a <hi>Nero,</hi> a <hi>Domitian,</hi> a <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula,</hi> or any power of the viſible world to ſcourge me: Give my back to the ſmiters, and let me know and ſee thou giveſt it, and then let me take pleaſure in it. For oh Lord, me thinks I ſee that a man may have a viſion of God, and may ſee a ſtar to ariſe out of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and may be convinced in his conſcience, that the earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof, and that God is the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94878:27"/> alone Lawgiver, Judge, and abſolute ſupream (as many, or moſt of the Nationall Prieſts and Lords confeſs) yet at the requeſt of a baſe ſenſitive luſt, and diviliſh deſire, will endeavour to have Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars built; yea, Altar, upon Altar, to ſee whether they can curſe the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God. Let us proclaim a Faſt, that ſo God may hear our Prayers, and grant our deſires, the longing of our ſouls. But Lord, how far is this from the true life of Saintſhip, and love in the World? But O Lord refine me, and then let me walk as refined.</p>
            <p>Thirteenth, The mandates of the Scripture (even the Scriptures from which the Potentates, and powers of the earth have, and do maintain perſecution and violence to others) do all of them extend to the Magiſtrate, and if he were in a Chriſtian conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution (as he pretends) he ought not in that relation to uſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall weapons, neither will he, unleſs he ſuppoſes himſelf wiſer then ever <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or an Apoſtle was, or hath received the Spirit more then an Apoſtle had, or hath received the Spirit to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and defend ſuch a practiſe, as the Apoſtle could not, neither did, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. Chriſt ſaith, when they were perſecuted, ſhould pray, when curſed, bleſs; Chriſt could have had twelve Legions of Angels to defend him in this viſible world, but he would not take any inviſible glory, or viſible excellency of God to defend him: And if the Magiſtrates will tell us plainly, that they have that power given them (as conſidered in a conſtitution of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and truth) which the Father would not give <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Son, or which he would not aſſume or exerciſe, nor give his Apoſtles power to aſſume or exerciſe: Let them prove, that they, or this, or that particular Magiſtrate had, or have, that which neither of them had, neither <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> nor Apoſtles: And let thoſe whom they are pleaſed to call Hereticks, and to baniſh, impriſon, and afflict; ſee their Arguments, that they have in themſelves, as in the preſence (though they think it not, nor perceive it, or know it, or though knowing it, will not acknowledge it) of the Eternall incomprehenſible Judge, non-reſpecter of perſons, the interioreſt, diſcerner, that can deſcribe that which man deſcribes with a fuller deſcription, and judge with a fuller judgement then man, or any viſible glory, or rationall intellect in the world; who is without the exterioreſt, and within the interioreſt, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94878:28"/> indiviſible in himſelf, who judges with a more abſolute judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then all the Councels, Potentates, Lords, Synods or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments of the earth. And when he enters into judgement, the fleſh of a Lord is no more then the fleſh of another man, nor ſhall more be juſtified by him, or be able to juſtifie it ſelf. But I beleeve, if things were demonſtrated in the world, according to the ſpirit of truth, reallity, and non-confuſion, the Lords, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates, and Counſels of the earth would appear to be the greateſt Anti-ſcripturiſts, though in words they would not have it ſo expreſſed, or ſo expreſs it themſelves.</p>
            <p>Fourteenth, Is it not a caſe of conſcience, or is there not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, that every particular man ſhould be perſwaded in his own minde for what he doth or for what he is commanded to do, leaſt he call good evil, and evil good, leaſt he call oppreſſing, perſecuting, Lords, Magiſtrates, Counſels, Synods, followers of the God of heaven in love, light and truth; Citizens of the New Ieruſalem, Saints of the moſt high God, livers in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, thoſe that walk with God? when indeed they are not ſo, but grinders of the faces of the poor; Idolaters, carnall, ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and diviliſh, having not the ſpirit, having mens perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage, making a prey of the poor and needy; having wiſdom, yet are not wiſe unto God, but to themſelves; oppreſſours (though not of their friends, or themſelves) of the Saints of the moſt High, or thoſe that are not perſwaded in their conſciences by the Divine Supream God: It is not ſtrange to ſay, know, and think, that magiſtrates (and miniſters ſo called) have been ſo, are, and may be ſo: The Scriptures of the moſt High God teſtifie it; the ſaints have wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed it, and ſtill do witneſs it with their blood and bodies: Are there not men, magiſtrates, and miniſters of ſuch mindes as <hi>Caeſar Caligula</hi> was of, that wiſhed that all the people of <hi>Rome</hi> had but one neck, that he might deſtroy many at once: Many can apply this: But Hell muſt inlarge her ſelf; Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign muſt be accompliſhed in Hell, as well as in Heaven; Saints give your backs to the ſmiters.</p>
            <p>In this my laſt Demonſtration and apprehenſion, I was in the concluſion, deſiring in my own ſpirit of that eternall <hi>Jehovah</hi> and everlaſting God, that I might be ſo ſwallowed up into that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:94878:28"/> eternall glory, wiſdom, power, will, that I might not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt my ſelf with my ſelf; but that my ſelf, or rather himſelf might be manifeſted in me, by me, and from me: then though the mutable Lords of the Aire oppoſe me, yet my alone ſubſtantiall, ever-remaining, ſupereminent Lord remaines: If I live he is, if I die, thoſe that live after me ſhall not truly ſay he is not, but he is the ſame. I alſo deſired that I might be ſo ſwallowed up to the life of the Lord, that in ſeeing of that Lord, in the things of that Lord, I might not reſpect perſons &amp; that it might be all one to me to be hated, and to be loved, to be honoured, and to be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, to have evill report, &amp; to have good report to be buffet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſcorned, contemned, deſpiſed, and to be counted the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of the world, &amp; to be courteouſly entertained, affected, delighted in, to be out of priſon when I am in, and to be in when I am out; to have all things when I have nothing, and to ſee only that all, that eternall wiſe God alone when I have any thing: if he ſhall call me to ſpeak of himſelf, that I may not live to any thing under the Sun, for I ſee vanity in all things; I deſired that I might ſee and live in the eternall life, in the life ſuperemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent: and if I ſhall be called amongſt the called Gods and Lords, that I might ſpeak, as ſeeing truly but one eternall God and Lord: For all the Gods and Lords of the earth ſhall wax old lik a garment, and ſhall be folded up like a veſture: this I know and ſee by experience. Thou Lord makeſt the lords of the earth their name to rot, and their memory to periſh, and what ſhall be to them in their ſeverall particulars everlaſtingly, thou LORD knoweſt.</p>
            <p>In companie I deſire to ſee thee, and to look up to thee in the underſtanding, as if I had none, that ſo I might ſee and not ſee, behold and not behold, be thou my alone companion. Here in the world men love one another, becauſe they are as to one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other according to ſence, but let me not be to any but to thee alone; let my life as the Apoſtle ſaid, be in the fleſh by the faith of the Son of God in the Spirit.</p>
            <p>In this world none muſt ſpeak of the God, but that thoſe the gods will approve of; none muſt ſpeak of the eternal, immutable, incondemnable, but thoſe whom the mutable, condemnable, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lords pleaſe, none muſt declare the eternal God to the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94878:29"/> world, but thoſe whom the Miniſters, or Synods of Nations, or the Gods of the Nation pleaſeth. But if thou abſolute, infallible miniſter, miniſtreſts to me, if thou committeſt a word unto me, inflame me, and let me be thy flame in the ſpirit, though the world indeavour to drown, to quench thy glory in me. But if I am not manifeſted by thee, let my hiding place be in thee, and of thee, ſo that let manifeſtation, and ceſſation; (to be, and not to be; and again to be) be all of thee, who haſt times and ſeaſons comprehended in thy ſelf.</p>
            <p>But Lord, if the lords of the earth impriſon me, viſit me in the underſtanding and lay not, if it be thy will, that ſin to their charge; for I deſire not to have pleaſure in their horror, when hel and death ſeizes upon them, I deſire not to be taken up with them, nor to live unto them, nor to rejoyce in their pains; for I deſire not to live unto my own pleaſure in me, nor any pleaſure to me, but be affected with pain to me from them, if thou wilſt it. But let me wholly live to thee but Lord thy will be done, for all things are of thee, all things are for thee, all things are to thee, though particulars ſee it not.</p>
            <p n="15">15. If it be ſuppoſed (as there is great probability to ſuppoſe) or if it hath been, and be known as by experience, that Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Lords, Potentates, Counſellours, Prieſts, yea high Prieſts, are ſwearers, drunkards, oppreſſors, walkers after their own luſts, blaſphemous, fallible men, will-worſhippers, (having none, as they ſay, to rule them) contemners, and deſpiſers of that which is good (unleſs it be from a Prieſt) from a Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſon, from a fiſherman; then Lords are you competent Judges? May not a man ſay to you when you would puniſh ſuch a one as you call a Heretick (though a man doth not countenance He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie no more then Chriſt did countenance adultery in the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, when they would have had her ſtoned) <hi>Let him that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin caſt the firſt ſtone at her;</hi> ſo you that are without Hereſie, or without the ſame Hereſie (for many times expreſſions of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality do make a difference) caſt the firſt ſtone, impriſon, deſtroy, baniſh, or take away the lives of thoſe you call Hereticks whoſe life perhaps may be better then ten thouſand of yours. <hi>But precious in the ſight of the Lord, though not of the Lords, is the death of his Saints;</hi> but you may do ſuch a thing in your dayes,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:94878:29"/> that you may never blot out of your conſciences, at ſuch a time, when you ſhall not be able to redeem your ſelves or others with ten Thouſands of Gold or Silver, or ten Thouſand Rams, or ten Thouſand Rivers of Oyl, or the firſt fruit of your body, for the ſin of your ſoul. But the Will ſupereminent, indeſcribable, is, that there muſt be perſecutors and perſecuted, crucifiers and crucified. Lords and high Prieſts look to your ſelves if you can: God hath choſen the poor of the world rich in faith: not many mighty, not many rich, not many Noble, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I exclude not all: What eternity hath done, that it ſelf knows.</p>
            <p n="16">16. A man for what he doth, eſpecially in a buſineſs of high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, had need be infallible, be abſolutely reſolved it is the minde of God as in Jeſus Chriſt, for if you live not to the ſupream Originall according to the of knowledg God, you judge the things ſo God with your own mindes, you judge the ſupream; ſo that it may be ſaid as well that the lords Judge the Lord as that the Lord judges the lords: But ye will not ſay ſo, will ye? neither wil you ſay you think ſo: but whether you ſay, or think ſo, you do ſo.</p>
            <p n="17">17. If you are infallible, your infallibility muſt proceed from the moſt high, immediately, truly, and underſtandingly; if you will declare things without the Scriptures (as you ſay you will not) if you will be abſolute Judges, if you will have Hereticks depart out of your coaſts, if you will have them baniſhed, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the minde of a Synodean Miniſter, who declared himſelf ſo to me) if you your ſelves are your own teachers, you will not ſay you are infallible; if the pretended Miniſters of the Lord Jeſus are your teachers, they will not alwaies be ſo audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (thanks be to the moſt High) to ſay that they are infallible, ſo that you ſhall finde great cauſe to confeſs you are at a loſs.</p>
            <p n="18">18. If your infallibility depends upon the underſtanding of the Scriptures, and ſo you (as you ſay) will walk according to the Scriptures, you muſt have the infallible Teacher to teach accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them, what is myſterious, and what not, to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the myſticall and the plain: if you acknowledge that there is a plain and a myſticall, and ſo to be more infallible diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers then others. Suppoſe a Noble man ſhould ſend a Letter to one that hath been an intimate friend of his in the Kings Army, and they having had precedent intimacy, know the minde one of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94878:30"/> another by this Letter, but when this Letter is intercepted, and comes to the hands of others, every man interprets this Letter as he pleaſeth; would you not eſteem it an indignity: when the ſupream Judge ſhall come to judge the world, as the Apoſtle ſaith according to his Goſpel, when the ſupream God ſhall averr in the interioreſt, and ſay, that indeed he ſent his Son, and anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with the Oyl of gladneſs above his fellows, and gave him the ſpirit not by meaſure, ſo that unmeaſurableneſs, and myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calneſs, was manifeſted in him, and by him, and he ſpake to a few Saints, and gathered by the power of the Spirit a few poor men to teach the myſteries of Chriſt: but there was one <hi>William Pryn</hi> Eſquire, a Lawyer, (I will not ſay Saint <hi>Pryn</hi>) and the Lords of the earth, and the Synods of the world proved interpreters with their own luſts, according to their formall, artificiall terms of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, and ſo they ſaid, this muſt be the meaning to day, &amp; this muſt be the meaning to morrow, <hi>Procul dubio;</hi> Lords, is this not indignity? But Chriſt will not be for ever crucified in his body the Church, crucifying will be over may be in time; but ſurely will, when time ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p n="19">19. If the Scriptures were ſo plain, that he that runs may reade, &amp; he that barely reads may underſtand, to what purpoſe is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit promiſed to lead into all truth ſince the Aſcention? If I may ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, knowingly, underſtandingly, infallibly, Aopſtolically, Chriſt like know and underſtand all that I ſee and heare concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my ſelf and others. But truly Lords and mutable Potentates, though you reade, &amp; hear, &amp; ſee (as you ſay you do) you may ſay as the Eunuch, how ſhall I underſtand without a guide? But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this, the guides ſay and confeſs they are not infallible.</p>
            <p n="20">20. If you do confeſs the ſpirit was promiſed to be given after the Aſcention, if it be given to ye, it is a greater glory for you to tell us of it, then laugh at it; to tell of it how it came to you, and when, then to tell us what you have done for us (if any thing) in relation to civils, <hi>Paul</hi> was not aſhamed of it.</p>
            <p n="21">21. If you confeſs that the ſpirit was promiſed to be given after the Aſcenſion, you had need to averr, juſtifie, and prove, that it was promiſed to be given to Magiſtrats, Lords, and Synods, not poore men, not Fiſher-men, that the ſpirit went from the poore, to the rich, from thoſe that the honourable count baſe,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:94878:30"/> to the honourable. And though it were ſo, it is no good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to convince a man, even to ſtrike him, to impriſon him, and defame him, as the falſe prophet did the true, when he ſaid, when went the ſpirit of the Lord, from me to thee.</p>
            <p n="22">22. If you prove that the ſpirit was to be given to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, Lords, Nationall preiſts, both you and the people had need know, whether you in this age, that now is more then any other, are the Magiſtrates, and the Preiſts. For it was not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to Magiſtracy in all Ages, if it had, it would have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, for he promiſeth nothing, but what he performeth. And that precedent Magiſtracy, have been enemies, and perſecutors of the Saints of God under the notion of Heretiques or thoſe that have been contrarie minded, it is playnly apparent, Hiſtorie declare it, and you your ſelves confeſs it, &amp; are convinced of it in your own hearts, as you ſay; therefore let that Magiſtracy as well as other men, let that Synod that thinks he ſtands take heed leaſt he falls, or is already fallen, or that he takes falling for ſtanding in himſelfe, and ſtanding for falling in others, and ſo judges, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes and perſecutes.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Me thinks I heare in my eares, a urge, ſaying, and a voyce to my underſtanding, declaring that there was a Nation or mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of people met together (as Epiſcopalls, Presbyters, and Independents, ſo called) and did convene from remote parts, the Eaſt, Weſt, North, and South, and theſe choſe ſome to conſult and debate what ſhould be for the good of that Nation, and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and gave them power, and honour, and externall glory, (ſo much as they could, or was in their power) but the prevayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing party tooke upon them the things of God, and the place of God, as much as in them lay, and beat and wounded thoſe that were contrary minded in their minds, as to God, though they ſtill continued loving and affectionate to them, Is this good? Oh! ſad requitall, may not you ſay, woe to your owne ſoul, for you have rewarded evill to your ſelves? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.12. Oh! my people, they which leade thee, cauſe thee to erre, and deſtroy the way of thy paths.</p>
            <p n="24">24. Suppoſe that a multitude of faire complexioned men, of ſtraite deportment ſhould chooſe and elect a companie, and place them in honour, and dignity, above themſelves, but theſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:94878:31"/> poore creatures, or ſome of them (may be <hi>Iob</hi> in the paralell) ſhould have an affliction upon them, their faces ſhould be chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, their bodyes ſhould grow crooked, and this ſhould be inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the God of all natures, mutable glories, and excellencies; or ſuppoſe God ſhould ſend <hi>Sathan</hi> to tempt them, or ſome of them, that they may conſent to the temptation, and whereas <hi>Iob</hi> had boyles, and ſores, even from the Crowne of the head to the ſole of the feet, would it not be ſad now, that one ſhould come and lay <hi>Iobs</hi> affliction more heavie on him, whipp the man, ſting him with ſcorpions? But would it not be as ſad alſo, to ſee two that were full of boyles, and ſores, wounds of <hi>Sathan,</hi> temptations of the Devill, that contrarie, that roaring Lion, in the ſhape of man, to whip one another, and laſh one another, for I have heard many of the nationall preiſts confeſs themſelves publiquely, that they have been full of wounds, and ſores, and putrifactions even from the crown of the head, to the ſole of the foot: Oh! Preiſt, it is better for thee to tell who healed thee, then to wound another that is in thy former condition, if thou art out of it, and truly tranſlated.</p>
            <p>But would not this make a man to breake out after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and ſay (O inhumanitie) had I knowne this, ſhould I have been ſo inhumane to my ſelfe; I am ſcourged, becauſe I am ſore wounded, becauſe I have boyles, becauſe I am in temptation, becauſe I am in errours, becauſe <hi>Sathan</hi> that politique Devill, that contrarie, hath deceived me, and I am deceived, though I have boyles, and ſores, from the ſole of the foot to the crowne of the head, ſent me of the God of Gods, and Lord of Lords, the Ruler of Princes, yet after the manner of men; I might have ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the rending, and tearing my owne bowells. I cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the heavens, and the earth, much leſs him that is greater then both, I cannot change my ſelfe, nor make him change me, till he will.</p>
            <p>But the will of eternitie be done, why ſhould I contend with the God of all changes? when I did chooſe them, I was weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it ſelfe: I was the weaker veſſell, and I am deſpiſed for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, yet I made not my ſelfe ſo, neither can I add one Cubit to my ſtature, reade 1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.30.31.</p>
            <p n="25">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:94878:31"/>25. Admit that thoſe that are generally called (and doe call themſelves) Miniſters of the Goſpel, and prophets of the moſt high God, in an eminent, and a ſupereminent manner, have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, and ſhould be told of God, as the Prophet was, what they ſhould do, 13 <hi>Kings</hi> reade the whole Chapter, muſt we goe forward, and backward, becauſe the Prophets do ſo. But ſurely I hope there is the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> in the way: I who am weakneſs, deſire of thee, O Immortall ſtrength, that I may more and more walke as comprehended of thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine will, that I may neither goe backward, and forward, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and backward, to the right hand, and to the left hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Nationall preiſts, and Prophets do ſo, but that I may walke as became a child to thee the Father of ſpirits, and the God of all conſolation, and therefore let me live to the willing life, and living will of thee, O ſuperſupereminent God.</p>
            <p n="26">26. Magiſtrates and miniſters of God (ſo called) you are but men ſubject to like paſſions that other men are, as well as an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle was (as he confeſſeth) if not much more; and you were not long ſince under Epiſcopacy, and owned it as of God, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you, if not all did: did you ſatisfie your ſelves, or were you ſatisfied of God? if you were, can you, or we that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary minded draw God to us to ſatisfie us when you or we will our ſelves, your ſelves?</p>
            <p n="27">27. You Magiſtrates and miniſters (ſo called) are but at the moſt, or the moſt you can ſay of your ſelves in your own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, is, that you are but wiſe and prudent men. But ſaith Chriſt, Father I thank thee, thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe, and prudent, Scribes, Phariſes, Lawyers, chief Prieſts, and revealed them to babes; but may be you will ſay now as <hi>Lloyden</hi> ſaid, the caſe is altered; but many Scriptures will prove this.</p>
            <p n="28">28. Magiſtrates and miniſters (ſo called) you ſhall die as well as other men: the King and the Beggar, the Fool, and the Achitophel, the maſter, and the ſervant, ye ſhall go to one Tomb that contains all generations myſtically in it ſelf: But I will not ſay you think you ſhall have a Pardon, or a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, or both.</p>
            <p n="29">29. Magiſtrates and minſters (ſo called) the Kings, the Prieſts, and the people; the beggar, and the rich; the wiſe, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94878:32"/> the fooliſh; the abaſed, and the abounding perſon; the Lawyer, with his terms, fallacies, and term-pleadings; and the Divines, (ſo called) with their formall, Sophiſtical Criticiſms ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear (if there be any judgement, as indubitably there is, and ſhall) before the abſolute perfect Tribunal, all the reſtitution of all things, when all things ſhall be brought forth, according to the will, powerfull Excellencie, and minde of the ſupream Cauſe, when the things that are myſtically, unſearchably brought forth, and are again myſtically hid in its proper center, in a way of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability, ſhall be brought forth in everlaſtingneſs; but this is a myſtery of eternity, at which time, and in which appearance, you Lords of the earth ſhall be judged in thoſe things that ye judge; queſtioned in thoſe things that ye queſtion others, and be your ſelves examined, whether you are in the faith, in a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperlaive manner. And ſo farewell mutable, dying, vain, unholy, unnaturall, temporarie, judging, inconſiderable man.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
